[MUSIC]
Okay, this is the YesWorkFlow annotation
of the script that was published for
LIGO as sort of documenting how you
do the detection from the data.
It's called LIGO Tutorial,
it's a Python script.
It's very nicely documented,
they have a Jupyter Notbook for that.
They have just the Python script itself.
And as a summer intern
project from last year,
a student here annotated that script and
created various products from that.
So we can look at that in more
detail in a moment as well.
So that's another example, and
then we have hybrid graphs.
We've also some no workflow graphs
in here you've seen before.
Okay, so
now let me jump into the actual demo.
So I'm going to my editor here, eMacs,
which is kind of my command line
environment among other things.
It's a browser and a command line,
everything all in one.
And so
I've cloned this white w idcc repository.
And in particular, where we want to
go is into the examples folder,
where the various use cases are.
So, we look at C3C4,
that's going to be our first example.
And then, we look at the second example,
the LIGO example.
We're going to look at those two.
But before branching into the sub-folders
where the examples live, let
me just point out a few others of levels
of other folders of this repository.
So there's a yw job folder.
Interestingly enough, the jar files,
the Java archive files for
the YesWorkflow tool are in here as well.
So probably you want to copy that to
a binaries folder where your system will
find it.
And so, this is of a detail that
has to do with the installation.
I don't want to get further into that.
But then here is a rules folder,
so that's interesting.
The rules folder contains data log
rules that have to do with the demo,
that do some of the demo functionality.
In this case, the rules look
a little bit like datalog rules,
but they're prolog rules.
So, we ship this demo, or we require
that when you install this demo,
you use a system called XSB prolog.
It's sort of a hybrid between
a datalog system and a prolog system,
it can kind of do both.
And this is, you see, for example, here is
used to create reports from provenance.
So this might as well be a Python script,
look at it.
It says print horizontal lines and
print Name, Description and so on.
So it prints out stuff.
So this is kind of plumbing for the demo.
Look at what is GV rules?
GV rules is a set of rules
that creates Graphviz files.
So what are Graphviz files?
That is the external tool that
we use to render the graphs.
So, we create a model, sort of a data
structure from the user annotations.
And that to render it maybe
in different colors and
different styles we use
an external tool called Graphviz.
Sometimes the files that Graphviz
uses as input are called DOT files.
We still have the extension
DOT which creates a lot of
confusion with Microsoft files.
I don't know, document templates or
whatever that stands for.
So we try newer versions of the demo,
we tried to create .gv files for
Graphviz, so we avoid the name
clash with the extension there.
So again,
these look like plumbing rules too.
They basically look inside here.
These are essentially print statements,
glorified print statements where we create
in a file, where we print into a file the
graph structure that we want to render.
And then, we invoke the Graphviz tool to
actually do the rendering of the graph.
I'm just going to walk you through some
of the sort of nuts and bolts of this.
Reconstruction rules,
okay there's not too much going on here.
Let's see, yw graph rules,
again these are views.
So these are a little bit more now
like datalog rules the way we already
know them.
So these are the rules and
then there are queries.
So, this is now closer to the user,
rated that user's question
against the provenance.
So, for example, if you say you want to
render the complete workflow graph.
And here is the program that
gets executed for this.
Okay, but
I think we're deep into the weeds, so
let's go into the particular example
folder that we want to look at, so C3C4.
You see each example has sub-folders, and
the structure of those sub-folders
is pretty organized as well.
But the thing that we first note is
there's a clean and a make script.
What the clean script does,
it basically deletes previous files
that were created from a previous run.
And then, the make script kind of makes or
builds the demonstration
artifacts files and so on.
Let's look at the clean script first.
You see what the clean script is doing.
It's basically looking some,
looking up some directory variables.
And then, it removes three folders, three
sub-folders for facts, views, and results.
So if they exist from a previous run, or
maybe through a check out of the code or
of the demo,
then we want to first delete them.
So let's do that, let's create a shell.
Editor likes to, it has its own mind
where to create those sub windows.
So, we're going to run this clean first.
So again, this is the folder in
which we are, we say clean.sh.
That was easy, not a lot of output there.
And sometimes this command line
demos are a little anticlimactic.
So, we remove some folders great.
Now let's look at this make.
Okay, the make is there's
a little bit more going on.
So let's just skim through it.
I'm not expecting you to really understand
the shell script, but just I'm pointing
out a few things so that you see
what are the ingredients being used.
So we're creating these folders, and
the folder names we get apparently
from the settings parent directory.
So let's just go up one level
to the settings, so in settings,
we've set lots of environmental variables.
We tell what is the example directory,
what is the project route.
We declare, for example,
facts directory and view directory and
result directories to be
wherever the example is living.
And then there are sub-folders for
facts and views and results.
If we've done a clean,
now we need to make those folders first.
And then what we do is we
run the YesWorkflow tool.
You notice there's sort
of a YesWorkflow command.
So how is that defined, yw command, cmd.
So you see we use, the YesWorkflow command
as defined as a environment variable that
has the value Java minus jar.
So we're going to run
the Java archive file.
And where does that come from?
Well that again is defined in
another environment variable,
which itself uses project root.
So it's heavily parameterized
to make things generic and
work across multiple examples and
also in a way expose really the structure
of this prototype and of this demo.
So we run YesWorkflow,
the command that we run is called model.
It means create a model, output a model,
well, what are the inputs?
The inputs are from the script directory
we take, in this case a MATLAB script.
Now this MATLAB script has
DCS workflow annotations.
We declare that the script
is written in MATLAB.
I mean it's kind of implicit
in the extension, but
we are explicit about it here.
And then we have to tell
to YesWorkflow also,
where should the outputs
from the YesWorkflow run go?
So we declare what is the extract,
the fact file and the models.
So where do the extracted facts go?
So you got,
basically the user annotations.
And where is the model itself going,
and what is the model?
The model is a graph,
how do we represent the graph?
As relational effects What
kind of relational facts,
we could use SQLite or any SQL facts?
But here we'll use this .P for Prolog,
because we can run
recursive queries on them.
Everybody who's done recursion in SQL
knows how tough this can be sometimes.
And for our purposes, running powerful
queries in XSP is much easier.
You can do everything from plumbing
to actual declarative queries to
recursive prolog queries, we can all
do it in this one system called XSP.
And so we declare that the query engine
in fact is XSP because that's what we
want to use subsequently.
And then we run a script that says,
okay, materialize to views and
then that goes somewhere.
And then we run another command,
ywmetlabreconcommand.
So what is that?
There is another Java file that we run for
that.
And on it goes.
And then eventually, we draw graphs.
Here's that doc tool or graphics tool.
So the command itself
is actually called dot.
The package itself is called graphics, but
the executable command is called dot, so
you have to have dot installed.
So you can then, in the previous step,
the dot file was created and now you can
render the graph itself and you can
render it as a PDF file or as a SVG file.
So here's in particular the command.
What this is saying,
go to the queries directory, look for
a script called Render
complete workflow graph and
this script will output or
generate a graphics file.
So that's the extension .gv.
That sometimes also called .dot,
confusingly.
So period D-O-T, again confusing for
many reasons including
because the operating system might
think it's a Microsoft dot file.
So that's why we call it .gv, and
then we call the dot tool to read that
just generated file, and create a PDF
file from it, as well as a SVG file.
So one is good to look at in the browser,
the other is good to look
at in the PDF viewer.
And then there are particular queries.
We just number them here, query1,
query2, 3, and so on, and
several of them are prospective
problems queries.
And some of them are I think, well not
here in this folder, hybrid queries, okay?
All right, so
let's run the demo after this sort
of somewhat lengthy introduction.
So we already have seen what happens
when we run the clean script,
now let's run this long make script
that makes all these things.
We wait a moment while all of
these commands are being executed,
and we are done.
Okay, that is very exciting at this point.
A script has been executed, no error was
reported, but the good news is we can now
look into those various folders to find
what the script has generated, okay.
So, again this is a demo where
sort of lots of queries have been
assembled together.
Everything is executed sort
of in one batch, if you like.
So let's navigate those folders.
So first of all, I'm showing this inside
of Emac so I can use it as a file browser
and I could look also
at the execution time.
We see at 10:37,
there's results folder and
the facts folder and the views folder were
kind of touched, so these are brand new.
Let's go first to the results folder and
maybe cut to the chase.
And you see there's all these files
that have been created at 10:37.
Just going to open slightly,
how do you say,
optimistically all GV
files that were generated.
So there are 14 graphic files that
have been generated by this script.
So, apparently 14 questions were asked?
And let's look at the answers
of those 14 questions.
And here they come.
So they're being opened and this certainly
could be improved in terms of explanation.
These are the answers, but
what are the questions?
We all know 42 is the answer, but
what was the question for that?
Right, you might recall, anybody read
The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy?
Not the right audience, okay?
So here are the answers,
let's look at the question.
The question is given away a little
bit in the file names here.
So, here we see workflow
upstream of grass fraction data.
What does that mean?
It means,
it is the workflow upstream of this output
product called grass fraction data.
Another way to say that,
we can say that's the lineage,
that's the data lineage
of grass fraction data.
Grass fraction data,
according to the model that we've created,
depends on only one input,
called SYNMAP, land cover map data.
It does not depend on all these
other files that you've seen before.
Yeah then, mean temperature and
mean precipitation data.
It does not depend on that.
Why does not it depend on it?
Because as you can see it in the graph,
the other inputs are not mentioned.
So it just depends on it,
it only depends on this one thing.
And how does it depend on it?
Well, there's a step called fetch
sinmap line covermap variable, okay.
So first we apparently fetch this data and
then we generate the next CDR file for it.
Is there any other input
that we need to consider?
Yes, if you go to the right,
there's something called grass variable
which comes from a step called
initialize grass matrix.
So really, there's one external input
that feeds into this grass fraction
data output, and then there's [INAUDIBLE]
internal data called Grass_variable.
And we could now go to the script and
try to look more closely
what the code actually does.
But we have a high-level conceptual
overview, so that's one of the products.
Here we see upstream of C4 fraction data.
Now upstream of C4 in some
sense looks similar, but
now there's kind of more stuff going on.
So C4 fraction data also
has this step generate
material file, but in this case for C4.
And then also we have this length
cover map variable dependency,
so we have that as well, but
we don't have the grass fraction,
Actually we have the dependency on SYNMAP
blank cover map data, but the grass
fraction output here is not there and
some of its details are not here.
That grass, to initialize,
remember the initialize grass metrics?
That's not here on this diagram.
C3's just the same as C4, apart from the
fact that it's the output is different and
the last step is different.
So basically,
you could now begin to compare,
how does the lineage of this
data compare to the other?
You could do sort of
a graph diff if you like.
What's the same and what's different?
That would be an interesting question.
Tell me how C3 fraction data and C4
fraction data are the same or different.
You could maybe grey out
the parts that are the same and
highlight the parts that are different.
No?
Okay, now whenever there's
something orange going on here,
then this is the hybrid providence,
where we have sort of instantiated
some of the data elements as per
the available files on disk.
And as we have linked them
to the ES workflow model
by way of these uri templates.
So you might recall that
there were uri templates,
let's look at the script again itself.
To make that connection very clear.
So we go here to the script subfolder and
here is the actual script,
the MATLAB script that we've
been asking questions about.
And whoops, it zoomed out again.
And if I look at these URI templates,
I see that they are in multiple places.
So for example, the grass fraction
output is over here, this file.
But there are also inputs, yeah.
So for example here,
the monthly precipitation probably and
the monthly air temperature over here.
They are declared through a variable.
And actually,
let me see whether I can create this also
quickly ad-hoc in
the workflow user interface.
If I change the scripting
language to MATLAB.
This is for the syntax, okay.
So here, so this is now the browser,
right, I just ran that in the browser.
And you see here these URI
template variables, you see that?
Let me zoom in even more.
See how's that, yeah.
So these are the UI templates
that I declared in the script.
And those are really valuable hooks that
connect the conceptual model to the files
that this code reads and writes.
And you see over here is a part,
when we ask for C3 and
C4 fraction data input, there's
a part that we don't reach from here,
like generate netcdf file for
grass fraction.
These guys over here don't care about it,
they don't care about the grass variable
and they don't care about this step.
On the other hand, they do care about the
latitude and the longitude variables and
so on.
Okay, so back to the script.
So this is what we've seen.
And now this helps us understand
these diagrams that we're looking at.
Okay, let's look at this one here.
This is what I mentioned before again,
this file was just created
from sort of the demo facts.
And we see that this particular
output file depends,
according to the model, and
according to the reconstructed
problems that was found on disk,
it depends on 25 files.
And when you look closely,
you see this precipitation data.
The file name is actually APCP.
Now we know it's precipitation,
[INAUDIBLE] rain.
The years are there, between 2000-2010.
And per month.
This is not sorted nicely, but
you see there's 12 of them.
So these are 12 netcdf files.
And similar for air temperature.
And so these are really the products,
and there's quite a few more.
And again, the file name
here gives away what the question was.
So again, this is a prototype.
Of course you could maybe embed this
as a little text in the graph itself.
Or make this whole thing
more dynamic instead of
sort of a batch processing demo.
But for us, the important part
was that everything is there.
Okay now, what about this one?
Now, this one looks very different,
what is this?
Why does this look so different?
Any idea why this looks so different?
So we know that c3 fraction data and c4
fraction data depend on a lot of things.
If you look at the files,
it's even 25 files.
If you look conceptually,
it's three inputs.
But we don't see three inputs here.
Any idea?
Again, this is the answer,
but what was the question?
The question here was not what was
upstream of C3 or C4_fraction_data.
The question is,
what is downstream of mean precipitation?
This is a different question.
It's subtle, when you all look at these
graphs, if you only look at the graphs and
don't think more about it, you might
miss out on a lot of the finer points.
Normally, we're interested in sort of
the upstream lineage of an output.
We say, okay, here's an output,
what went into it?
Why, because maybe you want to
publish that output and
you want to just cut out
as much as you need, right?
You don't want to publish
more than you need, so
you output just that particular
product that you're interested in
together with everything
that you need to produce it.
On the other hand, maybe you know that
some of your input data sets was tainted,
there's some problem with it.
Now you have a different question.
Now you say, okay, what output products
are influenced by this particular input?
It's not the same question.
It's not the same graph.
So here you would say, well,
if my precipitation data has flaws.
Later we found out there was
something wrong with it.
But what are my products that
are now spoiled because of it?
And what we see here is
the C3_fraction_data and
the C4_fraction_data will be spoiled.
If you were to go upstream again, there's
many more things that C3 and C4 depend on.
But that was not the question.
The question here was, what is
downstream of mean precipitation data?
So what is the influence of this
particular input on outputs?
And then we see, well,
these are the paths taken.
So this is how this particular input
could flow into the output data products.
And if the input was problematic,
then maybe these two products have to be
recreated, but not the third, because
that's not influenced by this input, okay?
And of course, I was hiding this from you.
If you look at the file name, it is
called downstream of mean precipitation.
Well, it's text, so where is that encoded?
So somewhere in the query,
there's an encoding.
So think of it as an equivalent maybe
Datalog or SQL where you write a query
that corresponds to, take this node and
go downstream of it.
That's actually the query
being executed here.
And this is just a rendering
of the output subgraph.
But it looks very different from
the other graphs we've seen,
because it seems to be missing,
whoops, time to do other things.
My calendar likes to jump into the action,
not very nice.
So again, over here we see this
downstream question answered.
And we see that several items on the right
are missing, or upstream are missing.
But they're missing on purpose,
because we had asked another question.
Okay, so
let's go through the other data products.
What is this, downstream.
And so there's lots of
little queries in a way now.
So downstream of the latitude variable.
Again, this is a downstream query,
not an upstream one.
More downstream business.
This is the complete workflow graph.
Of course, this is sort of the user model,
with the only exception that the URI
templates are not mentioned here.
But it is the full graph.
And, again,
you can see when you ask an upstream and
a downstream question how
they would be different.
If you say, upstream of C_fraction_data,
you will get all the inputs,
mean precip, mean air temperature,
and SYNMAP land cover map data,
if you go upstream from C3.
But if you go say downstream
from mean temperature only,
if you only go downstream,
well, first of all,
all of this stuff on the right
you will never hit, yeah.
But you will get C3 and C4, but
you will not get grass friction data.
Also you will not get this stuff up
here that has to do with precipitation.
We just get the temperature stuff, yeah.
So again, depending on whether you go
upstream or downstream, obviously that's
a different question and you got different
answers, you shouldn't be surprised.
It's like asking about your offspring
versus about your ancestors,
not the same question.
But when you just look at the graph,
unless you say in the caption or
in the explanation close to
the graph what the question was,
you might read the graph the wrong way.
Very tempting or very easy pitfall
here because it's easy to
create these artifacts.
[MUSIC]