[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
Now, let's briefly summarize some key
notions we learned about this week.
We learned that the data quality is
usually defined as fitness for use.
The intended use, specifically,
what questions you may want to
answer with your data, determines
whether your data is clean enough, or
of high enough quality,
for the intended purpose.
We learned about a few key
data quality dimensions, and
in the optional readings posted for
this week, you can drill deeper into many
other aspects of data quality dimensions.
You also saw that we can structure
the overall themes of this course into
syntax and pattern based cleaning,
then, schema and semantics for
which we will use
a language called Datalog.
And synthesis, where we zoom out again and
look at the larger workflow of
which data cleaning is a part.
Related to the latter is the notion of
prominence or data lineage and processing
history, something that will turn our
attention to at the end of this course.
In week two,
we will learn about an important formulas
and tool called regular expressions.
Regular expressions allow us to
check whether the syntactic patterns
we find in data match
certain standard formats, or
whether they require
additional processing.
We will practice matching with regular
expressions in our first hands-on
assignment next week.
Regular expressions are also part of
the powerful OpenRefine tool that we will
work with in week three.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]