[MUSIC]
Okay, so what we want to do here
is to look at SQL(ite) by example.
We're going to run through a couple of
examples at a certain level of detail,
I'll try to go a little slow to
show you how SQL works by way
of a mini-tutorial that is quite nice,
from Software Carpentry.
So we're going to go to this website,
it's called sql-novice-survey.
We're going to go to this website and
in particular, so
the website itself is on GitHub,
that's quite nice, so
software carpentry has made all
its material available on GitHub.
So you can clone it from there, download
it from there but you can also look at
the website through the browser and
there's a particular link given here,
and when you click on that link,
what you see is that little tutorial.
So that's what we're going to do but
before we go there,
I just want to say a few
words about SQL itself.
So the Structured Query Language SQL, is a
very large language has been standardized
since quite a while, and it's really
the world runs on relational databases.
The language itself is based on
the relational algebra, and as we've also
seen, the relational calculus sometimes
called Predicate Calculus but
there's a particular version that's
very closely related to SQL.
The language itself has many parts and
we're going to look at only one part
in more detail which is queries.
But also it's good to know that there
are other parts for example the data
definition language contains
statements on how you create tables.
So for example there is a create table
statement that would allow you to
define the name of a table, the name
of a relation, the name of the columns,
the data types of the columns, primary
keys, foreign keys, other constraints.
There's a data manipulation language
that would allow you to define updates.
So when you for example say you want to
give every employee in the database
a raise, or you want to delete every
customer who has not ordered something in
a long time, maybe not such a good idea.
Or maybe you want to, if a customer is
deleted then maybe you want to delete
the pending orders,
that's maybe a better idea.
So that would be statements you can
find in the data manipulation language.
And data control language says
how to give access to certain
tables to certain users and so on.
Some of these features you
don't find in SQL(ite).
SQL(ite) is very different from
traditional database systems
that have meant for server based
data management where many users
simultaneously can access SQL(ite)
of your personal database.
But it's very powerful for
individual users and for
our purposes using data queries and
negative constraint checking,
it's a good first choice.
So we are going to look in
particular at queries in SQL and
SQL is sometimes also called
a declarative language of 4GL.
That means it focuses not how
a certain operation is executed,
but what is the operation
that you want to execute.
If you had to implement some
of these operations yourself,
say in Python or C or in another
programming language, Java, say.
You would spend all the effort
on writing data structures,
writing loops, writing indexes,
all of that and
easily lose track of what you want to
do is ask questions about your data.
So we call SQL a declarative language
because it allows you at a higher level to
ask questions about your data, and that's
what we going to see in the examples.
Just very briefly what are the basic
building blocks of the language.
So a typical SQL query looks like this.
There is a statement of the form select,
from, where.
And what are the different parts?
In the select part of the select clause,
we'll list the attributes
that we want to have output.
So we run a query against the bunch
of tables, one or more tables and
we specify some conditions.
So, from these relations or other tables,
that's where we select from.
The select clause itself corresponds
more to a projection of operations and
the relational algebra.
If you recall those of you who have
background in databases will know there is
a projectional operation of pi where
we project onto certain columns.
And these are the columns
on which we project.
And the where clause is where
we can specify a condition.
We can say well,
we're only interested in certain rows
that match maybe a certain value or
that are greater than another value,
this is also where we can define joins.
We want to say that this column
in this table should align,
be equal to another
column in another table.
So this select from where is
really a basic building block.
And once you get the hang of it, it's
quite intuitive to write simple queries.
And so today, we're going to
look at some simple queries,
and at some more advanced queries as well.
So again, the As are the attributes.
The rs here are the relations or
table names.
And the P is a predicate, it can be
complicated, it can have and or not,
we can even have a nested query inside.
But overall, just so for
those of you who are fans of
the relational algebra or math.
To get a first idea of how
a relation query is executed,
let's have a look at this expression.
You see here r1 x r2 x dot, dot, dot,
all the way to rk,
say if you have k tables or k relations.
What that means is you multiply out
these tables, what does that mean?
You build a Cartesian product,
or cross product, you look at
all possible combinations of all
the tables that you have questions about.
So the database system will not actually
implement it typically that way,
because that's very wasteful.
Imagine you have let's say,
just two tables, each has a thousand rows.
Well a thousand times, a thousand,
that's a million rows right there.
Or if you have three tables
with a thousand rows each,
you would have a billion combinations.
So one of the benefits of a database
systems to be clever about running this
query not by generating
a billion possibilities but
having a query plan that reduces
quite a lot what you need to look at.
How can you reduce that?
Well, for starters, there's this sigma,
this little symbol here, sigma,
which is a selection condition.
This selection condition
is actually this P here, so
you have conditions that
you apply to the columns.
So you might say,
okay I want the name to be, or
let's say a year,
maybe if a year column you want to say,
the year should be after 2000 or
before 2010.
Yeah, so, here you can specify these
conditions and then instead of looking at
these whole cross product, the system will
kind of evaluate those conditions early.
Database people say it, the selection
is pushed down into the query plan,
into the operator tree and so you get
a much more efficient query evaluation.
So this explains the from and the where,
which is basically the cross product, and
then the sigma, the selection.
And then finally, what is called
unfortunately select in SQL,
is really this projection,
where you say, well now we're really only
interested in a certain number of columns.
So maybe out of those 20 columns that my
three tables having when I combine them,
I'm only interested in two of them.
But then I can say, well, just to let
me that column and the other column,
all right?
So this is basically just as an idea to
give you a first idea how a statement
that is fairly readable in
SQL can be translated into
an internal representation in
algebraic representation than,
that the database can further optimize and
evaluate efficiently.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]