[MUSIC]
And now we jump into something new to wrap
up the topic of SQL, and that's recursion.
So I want to show you
some examples of that and
also motivate a little bit why
we do not recursion in SQL.
So let's get started with that.
Recursion in SQL.
Well, first of all, it's important to
notice that in first-order logic or
predicate logic, as we've called it, and
in the relational algebra as you would
learn it, for example,
in more detail in the database course, and
originally in SQL you
do not have recursion.
You cannot traditionally express
these recursive queries.
And that's a problem.
And the academic community,
the research community,
has been advancing one of the reasons for
putting datalog forward was as sort of
a simple query language that's very
close to logic that you can also study
theoretically, but also practically,
that would give you recursive queries.
But if you don't have that in SQL,
you have a problem.
For example, here on the right, you see
a part that's assembled from other parts.
So it's often necessary
in practice that you have
a bill of materials that tells you what
are all the parts that are in there.
And if you want to compute that,
you will typically need a recursive query.
Otherwise you can't in general sort of
walk through this hierarchy of parts.
So over here, this is hard to see, but
this is essentially the output of
an analysis of what the parts are.
So parts have sub-parts which
have further sub-parts and so on.
And sometimes you need three of them or
five or two.
And in the end you want to have
sort of this bill and say,okay,
these are the parts that I need
to make the whole assembly.
So you can look a little bit closer.
For example,
Wikipedia has a decent article,
from which I took this figure here,
explains what a bill of material is.
And this is very practically relevant.
I'll just show you one example,
which is also taken here from Wikipedia.
It's a product structure modeling.
So I don't know whether you can see
this here, but here for example,
we see that a car is made, of course,
of an engine and a body, and
the engine is made of other parts and
so on.
And this is, of course,
the normal assembly view.
But in practice you need to have also
quite a bit of other views, right?
You might have a service view.
You might have a design view,
purchasing view, sales view.
The objects that you sell here
are organized in different ways, and
you need flexible ways to
work with these hierarchies.
And again,
SQL is not traditionally good at that.
If you don't have recursion, you have
a problem because you cannot walk these
trees and you cannot assemble things.
[MUSIC]