[MUSIC]
Now let's look at one more example, and
that is that ligoscript it was
not the gravitational lens.
It had nothing to do with gravitational
lenses, which are fascinating things
as well, but this was gravitational
wave detection in the LIGO's experiment.
Okay, so let's go to shell we want to
go one direct tree up to examples.
So what examples are there, and
then we want to go now down on
level again into LIGO, okay?
So now we're on this LIGO folder, let's
have a quick look at the script first and
you see the script is called
GW 150914 tutorialuri.python.
Now we could make,
let's just look at this.
The first observation of gravitational
waves is made on 14 September 2015 and
was announced by the LIGO and
Virgo collaborations on February 11, 2016.
So they were sitting on this for a while
to make sure they got it all right and
writing the paper, and
doing all the things they have to do.
So they announce it in February 11th
inside us probably knew this once you're
earlier.
Making this a little
documentary about this and
the film maker of that documents where
you said the NCSA for launch today.
Okay, so
this is the data release with it and
there's a Python script that comes
with this, that you can run.
To show how you would get
the signal from the data.
And if you want to understand that,
you should use that study that
the sources run the program.
What we have done is we've taken that
script and we've also annotated it.
So you see here, the inputs and outputs.
Okay, that's case sensitive here,
and I don't want to mess this up.
So here for example I'm looking at the URI
templates, you see it begin in and
out of parameters.
So we've annotated the script, so we get a
visual version of the underlined workflow.
So let's run this again just like before.
So we are in, let's first run
the clean script, again clean probably
removes folders that we don't care
about and then we can run the make.
That's going to take a little moment
to execute the various scripts and
then we can browse the results.
Let's just have a look at that make strip,
how that looks like.
And it looks very much the same
as the one we've seen before,
only now the script is a little different,
I mean it's not that C3, C4.
MATLAB script it is a python script and
then the particular queries that
we are running are also
slightly different.
But they're really, essentially
the only thing that is different,
the queries are fundamentally the same
questions that we are asking,
only these are specialized
to now a particular node.
So when we write these queries
we have to initially say,
this node upstream of that node and so on.
So if you were to do a dif,
actually that's an interesting exercise,
why don't I do this?
That's might be instructional.
So this is the demo script that
builds the products of the demo
in one case for the C3, C4 case and
the other case for the LIGO,
case as to a little dif and
then you can see the differences
and you see there a couple of
differences here and there.
There's a lot that's also the same, yeah.
It will require a little bit
more time to get into this, but
you see sort of highlighted here for
example if you render the work
flow graph even the type is the same yeah,
workflow is spelled as a rough craw
at a common transposition.
And you see that it's
essentially some of the parameters have
changed other than it's rather similar.
So there's actually not a lot of
differences between those two scripts.
This is only meant to assure you
that the demo is fairly generic,
you can apply it really,
it's not sort of one
example is very different from the other,
it's very much the same.
And so now let's look at the results and
let's do maybe a similar brief thing as
before we're going to
mark all the GB files.
Now we have 23.
So the LIGO demo has even more artifacts
being generated before I think it was 14.
So let's have just a quick
look at what those are.
Okay lots of files are being generated.
Okay, lots of different questions and
as usual, the question being
asked is somehow suboptimally maybe but
it's encoded in the file name.
So if we're interested in a data output
program that's called whitened bandpass
wav file, and
we want to know well what goes into that.
This what we seen in the front,
here in the center would have the answer.
This is upstream of
whitened bandpass wav file.
First of all, notice that this is a
prospective prominence graph or a workflow
graph, because it doesn't have this
slightly darker orange sort of instances.
So it says that at the schema level if
you like, well at the workflow level,
the whitened bandpass wave
file depends on three things.
The sampling rate and detector,
and then this parameter called
fs that we could now look up in
the tutorial what it stands for.
I think those are the two, h1 and
l1 correspond to the two detectors,
two instruments.
And again these are the steps, so
this gives you a good idea how this
particular data product was created.
That is your prospective provenance for
this particular data product.
So this, the order in which these products
are shown here Is probably somewhat random
upstream of spectrogram whitened,
that looks very similar.
Personally I would not allow to ask
the question what's different between this
graph and the other one that we just saw?
So a corresponding question
could be written and programmed,
we haven't done that, but
that wouldn't be very difficult to do.
You can say I have this one,
I have that one, what's the difference?
Might be a little project right there,
and what's upstream of the spectrogram?
This looks much smaller, yeah?
So this is a product that doesn't
depend on all of the other things.
Upstream of the shifted wav file,
again that has more stuff.
Upstream of the filtered white noise,
that has less things again.
And again, creating a difference between
these might also be interesting.
So let's look at some data products
tat are really much more differen.
Well these baby graphs we
don't even take for serious,
upstream of coefficients, okay.
I think this demo just basically look for
all the products, what's upsteam of them.
But here's an example that's interesting,
because that has now what
we called hybrid problems.
So there are three output files generated,
and
these seem to depend on these input files.
So now we have to instantiate once again
into the sub-schema level
prospective problems graph,
retrospective problems information
about the files being read and written.
So these input files are read and
these output files were written.
So this is similar to what
we saw before in C3,C4.
And here is the complete recon graph.
You see, so these are all
the outputs being produced and
all the files being produced.
So shifted wav files, we have three.
Stray data, data we have one.
Wave file, we have, again, three.
And here there are various inputs and
intermediate products, okay?
Okay, so I think I'm going to leave it
at that for the downstream queries.
Again, they look like
graphs again like before.
But now we see that they
are somewhat different structure,
because if you want to know,
well if my data is spoiled and
the data that I have is strain L1,
whitened bandpass,
maybe what can be influenced
by it going downstream.
There are three files,
three outputs, three elements.
It could be more than three files
because again this is the schema.
And here is the complete workflow
graph with your UI templates.
This is interesting maybe,
because this is the whole enchilada
if I can use that term here.
It's a technical term,
the whole enchilada.
It's the whole prospective prominence
graph generated from the model.
So this is a nice artifact
to have to understand,
what is really going on in that script,
and although this is still complex.
It makes very clear what is
the data flow between the steps.
It's a good way to communicate
with people, what's happening,
and at the same time ask questions
about dependencies if you have those.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]