Welcome back. In this week's lectures,
we have seen different aspects of workflow modeling and
provenance coming together when using the YesWorkflow toolkit.
YesWorkflow can be used to model, render,
and even query both prospective and retrospective provenance information.
While in the beginning of this course,
we started out with different aspects and dimensions of data quality,
focusing on ways to check and improve syntactic and semantic data quality,
we have now come full circle.
We have seen how workflow techniques can be used not only to automate repetitive tasks,
say we have workflow systems or conventional scripts,
but also how basic notions,
such as provenance, and tools that support modeling,
capture, and querying of provenance can be used to improve transparency of data analysis.
Ultimately, the use of provenance techniques and tools such as YesWorkflow contribute to
the transparency and reproducibility of data wrangling and analysis pipelines,
and thus help that newly generated data is of good or at least known quality.
But no matter what the quality is of the data you are working with,
we hope that some of the tools and techniques you've learned about in
this course will help you in tackling your next data wrangling job.
And while an increasing number of ever more powerful tools is becoming available,
many of the underlying principles such as pattern-based cleaning,
integrity constraints and queries,
or workflows and provenance will be
useful no matter what specific tools you will be adopting.