Hello everyone, welcome to CS 421.
This week we're going to take a break
from what we've been doing before,
we're going to introduce some theory.
So in this one we're going to
talk about semantics.
Semantics comes from a Greek
word which means meaning, and
this is the mathematical study
of the meaning of computer
programming languages and
their constructs.
So in order to do this, we're going to
introduce three different things.
One is called a judgment, which is
something that asserts a property about
a piece of computer code or programming
language, construct or syntactic object.
We have proof rules that define
when judgments are valid, and
these are recursive inductive objects.
And we have proof trees which will look
like proof rules stacked together to prove
properties about something more complex.
Now this treatment of semantics is
borrowed heavily from Robert Harper's
book, which I cited the last slide.
And I highly encourage you to take
a look at that book as a different
way of approaching programming
languages which you may find helpful.
So judgment is simply an assertion about
some syntactic object we're interested in.
So for example,
we might want to talk about whether or
not numbers are even or odd.
Here, three is odd could be a judgement.
I am asserting that
three is an odd number.
Here's another judgement.
This is something called big steps
semantics, and here what we're
saying is that two plus three, and
then we have this down arrow, five.
And what this is asserting is that
two plus three is equal to five.
We have this thing,
which comes from typing semantics.
We'll talk more about what the funny
T on its side symbol is later.
But this is just saying that
if you have the expression,
2.4 greater than 3.5,
then this is a boolean type of expression.
When we have judgements, we want to be
able to say when a judgement is valid or
when it's not valid.
I mean you can just write down
any judgement that you want but
how do you know it's true or not?
How do you know it's accurate?
I could have written down, for
example, that three is even and
that would be false.
So we have these definitions,
these are called rules,
which tell us when a judgment is true or
when a judgment is not true.
So the way it works, you have this thing
that looks kind of like a fraction,
it's not a fraction.
But you have this horizontal bar, and on
top of it you have a bunch of judgements.
Now these judgements are called
assumptions or premises, and
on the bottom you have a final judgement
which is called the conclusion.
And the idea is if all of the J's on top,
J1 through Jn,
are true then J on
the bottom is also true.
And often on the side you will also see
a label which gives a name to this rule,
and this way we can refer
to it easily later.
It's possible for a rule to have
no assumptions whatsoever, and
this is called an axiom.
And in that case, what will happen is
you'll just have a rule with a line and
nothing on top.
You'll just have the conclusion and
perhaps its label.
Another thing that you can see is
something called a side condition.
Here is an example of an axiom here,
except it has a side condition.
So you have this thing,
x mod 2 equals 0, on this side.
Now sometimes you'll see people put
that as one of the premises, and
there's nothing really wrong with doing
that, it's kind of a style issue.
But the reason we put it on the side and
not on top,
the idea is that the things on top
of a rule should be judgements.
And in this case,
what we're thinking of as a judgement, or
maybe I should say what I was
thinking of as a judgement,
is just the assertion that something
is even or something is odd.
So if it has that form, then it belongs
either on top or on bottom of this rule.
But if it's something different, if it's a
condition that's not really a judgment but
it's something else that needs to be true,
then I call that a side condition.
And so a lot of people will write
that on the side of the rule instead.
So you'll see both of them.
And if you go looking at
papers about semantics,
this one I think is slightly more common.
And here's an example of the even and
odds again.
This time I've given rules for
what happens when you add even and
odd numbers together.
I'm sure you're familiar with this
from your studies of arithmetic,
but you know if you have
two even numbers and
you add them together you get another
even number, so we have this rule here.
If x is even and
y is even then x + y is even.
Similarly for the other combinations
of even and odd number editions.
Now before we go to next slide I want you
to pause and see if you can write down
the rules for what happens when
you multiply even and odd numbers.
So go ahead and do that now.
All right, so here is the solutions.
Pretty much any combination of even and
odd multiplications gives
you an even number, unless of course both
the numbers happen to be odd already,
so that's what these rules are saying.
But when you use a rule what
will happen sometimes is that
the bottom thing is complicated
enough that the two assumptions, or
however many assumptions on top,
also need to be proved.
And so you use more rules, so
it ends up having a recursive structure.
And so this builds something
that's called a proof tree.
Now two ways that proof trees get used.
One of them is that you have something
that you already know what the property is
but you just want to prove it.
So here have 4 + 7 is odd, and so
I already know that is a fact but
maybe I want to convince you, and so
I'll go ahead and build this tree.
I'll show you that four is even,
and I'm using the mod zero rule.
And I justify that because
four mod two is zero.
I have seven is odd using
the mod one rule and
I justify that because
seven mod two is one.
And then I've also written down that
I've used the even plus odd rule
to show that 4 + 7 is odd.
When this happens, you'll see the proof
given as a finalized construct.
Now how do you go about writing
a proof tree in real life?
Typically what will happen is you'll start
by writing down your conclusion, and
then you'll draw a line on top and
decide what rule it is you want to use.
And then what will happen is you'll take
the parts of the thing you're trying to
prove and you'll move them up and use
the appropriate rules to talk about them.
So here I have to move up the four and
say that four is even,
then move up the seven,
say that seven is odd.
It may be also that you don't
actually know what the property is.
Maybe you're not sure if 4 + 7 is odd or
even.
And so what will happen is you'll
leave some information out,
you'll go ahead and
follow what rules seem appropriate.
And as you do that you're
going to discover information,
you're going to fill that back in.
We'll talk about how that works in future
videos, but I'll tell you that the type
inferencer that Haskell uses
works in a very similar way.
So here again is that book I was
telling you about by Robert Harper,
Practical Foundations for
Programming Languages.
He has a different take on languages
than what we're using in our course,
so there's of course a lot of overlap.
I would definitely encourage you to take a
look at this book, it's very interesting.