[MUSIC]
Welcome back to Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
In this video I want to introduce
the relational model and
to show how we can work
with relational data.
So first,
let's put us in the context however.
So, we started out with
regular expressions.
We were looking at synthetic issues.
How can we use regular expressions
to define patterns for matching and
extracting data?
In this way using regular expression
we were able to check the conformance
of certain data strings in our raw data.
For example, whether our data was
conforming to the ISO date format,
which is four digits for the year,
a dash, then two digits for
the month, another dash, and
then two digits for the day.
If the data does not conform to
this structure, to this pattern,
then we would bring it into a canonical
form, for example, using a script.
Another tool that we've learned so
far is OpenRefine, which uses regular
expressions, but is In general a much more
powerful tool we can use to profile and
clean data, one column at a time.
So one particularly powerful
feature of OpenRefine
was the use of
similarity-based clustering.
But in the end we were working
with OpenRefine to clean up
data in a single column and bringing
the data then into a canonical form.
But what about a more complex issue that
span multiple columns in our data tables?
What about logical errors?
How shall we deal with this kind of
data quality issues at the schema and
that the semantic level.
So here's an example of you seen
before where we have two tables,
a Person table and Address table and
some of the data quality issues should
have been address with OpenRefine.
But even if you have cleaned
your data using OpenRefine,
some other kinds of issues about dirty
data can still make it into your tables.
So how shall we deal with those?
For example, you might have integrity
constraints that span multiple tables,
maybe a foreign key that goes from
the person table to the address table or
maybe you have duplicates.
Or maybe you have some illogical
contradictions in your data.
So never mind the pattern issues,
the syntactic issues,
that OpenRefine addresses.
What about the semantic and
structural issues?
Issues at the schema level, when we
load data into a database we can than
use the database technology
to deal with those issues.
So here's an overview of our work flow,
simplified overview.
So we started out with raw
data that is often dirty and
then we use a tool like OpenRefine to
do some sort of pattern based cleaning,
again using regular expressions,
using clustering and so on.
The next step, we can then load this data
once it has gone through this initial data
cleaning, we can load it
into a database system.
And once the data is in a database system,
we then can exploit the powerful database
technology to run queries and
to check integrity constraints.
So this will be the focus of this video.
How shall we go about doing this?
First, we have to understand what
are relational databases and
what is the underlying data model,
the relational model?
We will then look at query languages,
in particular we will look at the logic
base approach first called Datalog.
And we will learn about the facts and
rules and queries and
integrity constraints in another video.
Another advantage of looking at Datalog is
that there's a very rich body of research
both in theory and in practice.
So Datalog while not as widely use as SQL,
has still found niche applications
including an industry.
And then finally we will move on to look
at the really dominant database query
line which in the real world which is SQL,
the structured query language.
On the right, you will see again the
overall workflow that we follow here from
raw data through pattern based
data cleaning with OpenRefine
into database system which then
will allow us to use queries and
integrity constraint mechanisms to
check the logical quality of the data.
So, here we need a little refresher, or
if you like, a crash course,
on the relational model.
So data is often organized into relations.
We might know this from spreadsheets.
But when we think of the relational
model in the context of databases,
we have a very particular model in mind.
The database model called Relational
Databases was pioneered by Edgar Codd in
the 1970s.
So it's been out there for quite a while,
but it's been an industry standard and
sort of a leading technology ever since.
So how is data organized
in the Relational Database?
Well, first we have data in relations or
tables as we call them and
then the tables are organized
into rows and columns.
Typically we really think of
them as organized into rows, or
tuples sometimes, and then the columns
are sometimes also called attributes in
the Relational Database world.
And we can then distinguish the first
row if you like which is very special,
which is the header or
schema level information from the body or
the actual instances which
contain the actual data.
Some more terminology in this context, so
we're really focusing today in this
video on the Relational Model, and
then a Relational Schema is really
the kind of header information,
the set of attributes, so the tables or
relations, their names and
their attributes, and then the Relational
Database instance to make it clear.
We can say the word instance, so the
Relational Database instance consists of
the data itself, the particular rows that
are spread across all these columns.
And last not least, RDBMS stands for
Relational Database Management System.
Those are of course the systems
on which we run the actual
queries that we're interested in.
So if you more worked in
the Relational Model,
the Relational Model is really close
closely related to predicate logic.
Sometimes also called first
order predicate logic.
So although it was in some sense invented
as a technology in the 70s, the underlying
foundations of the Relational Model
are even older than that and
they are in some sense the foundations
of our logical thinking if you like.
A very particular model to
which the Relational Model
is closely related is used for
conceptual modeling and
that's called the Entity-Relationship
model or Model.
So here in the slide you see at the center
left a thumbnail of such as an Model.
The key idea here is that we
structure the world into entities and
relationships that model
our application domain.
This is a very simple yet
very powerful model.
Look at the first idea of the things
that you want to store in the database.
And there are many tools that
allow you to go from an Models or
from a conceptualization
of your application domain
automatically to a relational
database schema.
So you can create tables from your
Relational Model automatically
with many tools.
The Relation Model is also very flexible,
it allows us to represent for
example XML data,
graph data, or object data.
And in fact there are extensions
to relational databases that
support these particular variants of data
models in a very efficient way such as
object relational databases.
But the main reason why we study
the Relational Model here is because it
allows us to use queries against
the relational data that we have and
therefore check the quality and
integrity of our data.
So, the relational model, for the purposes
of this class is really interesting,
because we can query that data and
run checks on the data and
ask questions about the data.
So what are the query languages
that are typically associated with
the relational model?
Well, as I already indicated,
the Relational Model is closely related
to first order predicate calculus,
sometimes called FOL, or just FO,
or RC for the relational calculus.
Then, this relational calculus or
first order logic, is not extremely
convenient for really writing practical
queries against the relational database.
So there is a much more intuitive rule
base language called Datalog, and
it is this language Datalog that we will
be using to run our first queries and
integrity constraints against a database.
From a database course which
this is of course not, but
from a database course you would know and
learn additional query mechanisms,
in particular the Relational Algebra,
here also abbreviated as RA.
And the Relational Algebra is the first
step of a database system to go from
a query, from a high level
query into an execution plan
that the database system can optimize.
And the query language most commonly
used for querying relational data is,
of course, SQL,
the Structured Query Language.
And although it is outside of the scope of
this course to give a deep introduction
into SQL, we will do a brief review
since we will need SQL to answer some
of the questions about data quality and
integrity that we have in this course.
So, the main focus, again, for studying
the Relational Model is it allows us
to store all kinds of data
in convenient form, and
then we have a powerful query language or,
in fact, a family of query languages
that we can employ to ask
questions about the data and,
in particular, to check the logical
integrity of the data, and
spot errors this way using integrity
constraints expressed as queries.
On this slide I give
a high level overview and
connection of the different formalisms for
querying relational databases.
Much could be said about this but
I will just give a high level overview.
So we will look again at SQL,
the structured query language.
Which is basically structured as if
you would write a query in
stylized form of English.
So there is a form to express queries
in this something like select
certain attributes or
columns from certain relations
where certain conditions are met.
So this is the SQL query language.
And there is another
more theoretical language
that is used in the implementation
of relational databases, and
that you also study in a database course,
it's called the relational algebra.
And it has mathematical
operations that work on tables or
relations as we call them.
And then produce new output relations or
tables as a result.
So, you will see these Greek letters.
Sigma for selection, pi for projection.
Then you see a butterfly,
which is join operation, and a delta for
renaming or a row, in fact, for renaming
a union operator and a set difference.
So these relational algebra operators
are something that you would study in
a relational database course.
Closer for
us to home is the relational calculus.
Although we will not say
too much about it, but
it is the formalism used to query
relational structures in logic so
we see some symbols there, there's the
universal quantifier for all xF basically
when making a statement in logic and say
that for every x the following is true.
Then f is again an expression in logic
what can be an exteseteial qualifier we
can it is the case that
a certain thing is true and
then we have other logical operators for
and and or not.
Again it would go too far to go into
these in greater detail here but
it is important to know that the formal
under pinnings of the language
we do study data log are in fact
based in logic, mathematicians.
And logicians would be happy to use
the relational calculus or first order
predicate logic to express queries and
questions about relational structures.
As practitioners however, we're not so
happy with this formalism which is why
we use a language such as Datalog.
To make all of this
a little bit more concrete,
I have here on this slide
a very simple example.
So imagine you have a relational
schema that has two tables.
One table called the employee table, and
it has three columns called employee,
salary, and department number.
So the idea of the employee table is that
it stores information about employees,
their salary, and
the department in which they work.
And then there's a second
table called the DeptNo.
Which has, again,
an identifier for the department,
and then also a manager for
that department.
And you could imagine that the manager for
the department is himself or
herself an employee.
So there's two tables and
there's some connections between
Between these two tables.
And there might be similar
relationships even within a table.
And of course, we cannot use a tool like
OpenRefine that will not help us here.
So we really need to jump
into this database world,
then use query languages to
explore these relationships.
So let's say we want to ask a question, in
this case not yet an integrity constraint,
just a simple question about the data, and
we want to create maybe a relationship
between employees and
the managers that they work for.
How would we do this?
So we would look at the employee table,
we would look at the department table and
then we would bring together this
kind of information from both tables.
This is called a join operation.
So this is the butterfly symbol
in the relational algebra.
In SQL, we would say for example,
the following which is almost natural.
Language so we would say select an
employee and a manager so denoted here emp
and manager, from the two tables that
we have which is the employee table and
the department table but subject to
certain condition and the condition is we
want to say that the department
mentioned in the employee name table.
That would be the third column shall
be equal to the department number and
the department table which
is the first column there.
So, we have to have some sort of agreement
on the third column of the employee table,
and the first column, the department table
as these rows align and have the same
value there then we want to report who's
the employee and who is the manager.
That way we have joined the information
from those two tables and
have some sence uncovered or
revealed a new piece of information.
I don't want to go into the details
of the relational algebra here but
you see there are some sort
of mathematical notation
that tells us how these two tables
are combined to create a joint table and
then we project on some
results column of interest.
Even less pleasant maybe to the untrained
eye is the relational calculus or
predicate logic formula.
So I will not mention too much about
it but rather focus on the last
item here on this line which is
the Datalog rule because in some sense,
this Datalog rule says exactly
the same as all the other rules,
only that it is much more intuitive and
easy to understand.
So Datalog rule has two parts, the left
hand side and the right hand side.
On the left hand side in some
sense you see the conclusion or
answer to a particular question.
In this case the answer is a relation
called boss, so it is the boss or manager
table if you like which pairs together
an employee and the employee's manager.
And on the right hand side of
the rule we have the query condition,
the body of the rule.
That tells us how shall we find this
pair of an employee and a manager.
The body of the rule is intuitively
quite easy to understand.
It is, in some sense,
a logical pattern that describes,
almost by way of an example, how these
two tables are to be combined, so
we see that we picked from the employee
table, a triple of values,
three variables, Emp,
salary and department number.
And then the comma is really the logical
end, and we see it, well also in addition,
we want to have from the department
table a pair of values,
department number and the manager.
And here, it is important to understand
that the department number If we pick
the department table, and
the department number that we picked
from the employee table, call inside.
When those are the same, then we want to
report that fact and then in some sense we
apply the rules that are from the right
to the left and we report that we found
the pair between an employee and
the employees boss or manager.
So let's summarize what we've seen so far.
We started out with the syntactic
data cleaning operations that
we started in previous videos.
And we have now begun to venture in the
central part of this cause the schema and
semantics in particular we started
out with a relational model.
At least we understand that the relational
allows us to store all kinds of data
in a flexible manner and in particular
it will allow us to query and
ask questions about the data and check for
integrity violations and then report them.
And this will be the subject of the next
video where we'll talk about Datalog and
then subsequently about SQL.
[MUSIC]