[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome back to Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
Last week, we learned about our first
hands-on tool, regular expressions,
which we can use to check whether
data matches a certain pattern, or
conforms to a certain standard.
Regular expressions can also
be used in a power tool for
data cleaning that we are studying
this week OpenRefine.
In this week, we will talk about how
to normalize data, it is eliminates and
tactic differences in data such as
different spellings of names, places or
other entities.
Other differences for example, the use of
upper case or lower case letters Or mixed
forms of these, or the use of additional
white spaces, punctuation symbols and so
on can all be nicely addressed and
cleaned up with OpenRefine.
Specifically, we will learn about
common transformations in OpenRefine,
facets and clustering.
By collecting the different or
similar values in a cluster,
a single canonical name can be selected
to represent the single entity that
is referred to by the slightly different
spellings and syntactic variances.
The goal of this week is to enable you
to create a new OpenRefine project, and
load tabular data into the system.
After which, you can then apply
common syntactic transformations,
such as trimming white spaces.
And finally, you should be able
to use facets at clustering.
The letter is a particular strength of
OpenRefine that let's you normalize
different variations and
bring them into canonical form
which is really a prerequisite for
most subsequent data analysis projects.
When you master OpenRefine,
even at the beginners level, you will have
a power tool at your disposal that can
help you get your data cleaning job done.
At the end of this week, you will again
be able to test what you've learned
using your hands on
assignment using OpenRefine.
All right, so much for now and
let's go to the first lecture.
[MUSIC]