[MUSIC]
We think of a script as an overall box, so
there's an interface to the outside and
then on the inside, typically, we tell
more about the workflow on the inside.
This case on the inside
there's not a lot going on, so
It's really just this code
called print_greeting.
Just greet the program user, maybe we
want to see, we say program users,
you see it dynamically updates this.
It's actually fairly dynamic for
the fact that behind it is a somewhat old
fashioned clunky,command line
base tool called Graphis.
But, you know, the web set up is in such
a way that it uses micro service and
it's fairly efficient in that.
So greet the program user I can say,
maybe with an exclamation mark,
it's interactive this way.
If I had additional outputs,
I could create also more outputs.
Maybe happiness is another
side effect of this output.
And these annotations are done with this
ampersand sign, in, out, begin and end.
But they have to be inside of a comment.
So yes only looks inside of comments.
So since this is not inside of
a comment yet, ignores this.
Once I put the hash sign there,
it becomes recognized as a comment and
that's now why you see this output.
And I could say similar things like here,
I guess it's yeah stream standard out.
Could be modeled, why does it?
Okay so we have the first question.
Why does this output, why is that not
shown in the same way as this one.
Anybody see why that might be the case.
Actually, I don't see it.
What is different, between those two?
Find the one difference.
Okay, I see the difference.
So we're declaring that
the print_greeting step has two outputs,
happiness and greetings.
But the happiness is not declared
as an output of the overall steps.
This is like intermediate data.
But let's say we want to advertise this,
this is a global output.
Then we need to do a similar thing here,
we need to declare
another output globally.
And let's say maybe happiness is
something that we're going to export.
And again I'm writing it first without
the comment syntax so the system
doesn't try to proactively render it
while I'm still creating the annotation.
So once I've created the annotation I can
put the pound sign in front which makes it
a comment which make this workflow
react to it, so that it is, okay.
So now print greetings has to
outputs the greeting itself and
also happiness is somehow
created that way.
So let's loop before we move on or
before we finish up here,
let me just show slightly
more advance examples.
So here is the greetings example.
Now you see this is more
realistic workflow.
So it has three input, greeting is
provided, there's an emphasis and
then there's an emphasis count.
You see also a difference.
We can distinguish between data and
parameters.
This is something a script
could not tell you, why?
Because it's the eye of the beholder.
What is the difference normally
between data and a parameter?
We think of it in a model, we say,
well parameters are meant to change
the behavior may be of the system and the
data is the thing that's being consumed.
So there's some sort of a qualitative or
conceptual difference,
it's hard to pin down, and
that you wouldn't see in the code.
It's really in the way you think about it,
so we think of the emphasis count as
a parameter that changes
the behavior of the script.
Maybe if the emphasis count is ten,
you say print hello world ten times.
And if the count is three,
you put the three times.
That changes the behavior but
the provided greeting and
the provided emphasis are really
data that are sort of consumed and
in this case we use to
produce the desired output.
So in this case again you have
the very similar set up as before.
You declare the overall workflow and
declare the global inputs and outputs.
You see here are two inputs,
the provided_greeting,
the provided_emphasis,
and the emphasis_count.
And so you can interactively change that.
And there's a single output overall,
which is the displayed_greeting.
And then inside you will
have the emphasis_greeting,
which is this code block, and then the
print_greeting, which is this code block.
And you see in this case, there's a simple
loop that repeats a number of times,
your greeting, which is the greeting
plus the emphasis, yeah.
And so it goes.
Now, so you've created this model, again
it becomes an artifact that you can use,
and you can do certain things now for
free with this.
So you can display it maybe top down or
left to right,
yeah because this is in the system
modeled as a data structure,
you can tell it, tell the underlined graph
is tool to render it in different ways.
Or you can emphasize maybe just the steps,
so you switch off the data.
This is sometimes a bit confusing, which
button is on and which button is off.
So I clicked on data,
to switch off the data.
Therefore, I now see the steps.
The steps are really only two steps.
Or if I switch off the steps,
in this case, I must show the data.
And this, this is just the data.
Where I can have them
both connected together.
There is also another little setting
where you can switch off and
on the port to the outside.
Yeah, If you are not interested in the
interface to the outside you switch off
the ports, or you switch the ports on and
then you see that this workflow
has three inputs, one output.
Can switch off the title and some, okay.
So again, this is meant as a first
introduction to, yes, workflow and
here's the particular workflow or
script that we've looked at before.
It has this energy levels and
all of that good stuff so
you see there's a quite bit of code.
And in the realistic example the number of
annotations to the code
is actually not that bad.
In the toy example you see a lot of
annotation, very little code, in
the realistic example you would have lots
of code, and not too many annotations.
And then you get this rather
detailed picture here.
So, let's switch off the data for
a moment, and focus on the steps,
so you can see you get an overview
of what the script is doing already,
by just looking at the steps.
Let's actually switch off
the ports as well, and
we have a nicer cleaner picture here.
So, there's a step,
called, initialize_run.
At this point seems to be disconnected,
that's going to be an interesting puzzle,
how that factors in.
And then there's a connected component,
we load screening results,
we calculate a strategy.
And then we have two outcomes,
or two branches,
one is logging the rejected samples.
So these are the samples.
That we put in our machine but we said
well this is not a good enough quality.
I'm not going to use that to
make an image of that and
then the other ones are going
in the collect data set step.
And then we transform the images and
then we also log some other result.
So if I switch on this thing again,
lets zoom in a little bit to
see whether we can, 150%.
So this is a more detailed
view of the script,
lets test something in between,
okay so yeah.
So you see how the different steps
are connected through these data items.
You see a lot of white boxes here.
The white boxes are parameters.
Yeah, so we don't think of them as data,
we think of them as parameters.
And there's log files, and
here's something that I mentioned earlier
that might have gone lost before.
So I'm going to zoom into
this quite a bit more.
You recall that we talked
earlier about UriTemplates.
So what is a UriTemplate?
So conceptually what I want to say, here's
maybe a step called transform_images and
what transform_images does, it takes raw
images and produces corrected images.
Easy enough to understand
once we look at this.
But where are the raw images?
Well the raw images are sitting on a file,
it could be reachable via URL, but
in this case we are a file.
What is the structure or
where is the location of this file?
Well there's a run folder.
Which has a raw images sub-folder,
and now here the fun starts.
There is another sub-folder but
you see those curly braces,
you see how it says cassette -id.
This is a template variable,
this tells us that under the raw
sub-folder in the run folder,
there are these cassette id sub-folders,
maybe two, maybe one, maybe ten.
It also tells us that whatever that folder
name is, we're going to use that as
a cassette_id, so we can have
harvest that and figure it out.
Now within the cassette, every cassette
consists of a bunch of samples so
what are the sample_ids?
Well we go into the cassette folder and
look at the samples in there.
And so
this is the sample id that we can extract.
And then for each sample we might have
taken images at different energy levels
and this is indicated here so the folder
is actually called e10000 or e11000.
And so we cam extract just like for
the regular expression we could
extract the number after the e and
have that metadata.
So this is part of the model
that the user has to create.
So whoever wrote this script, right,
somebody writes the script, so
somebody is creating a folder structure.
And that same person
would probably be a very
ideal candidate to write
these annotations.
So basically declaring, this is what
I've done so it's an explicit step but
by doing so now the system can extract
that information and now work with it.
So if you look at the raw image and
then you look at the corrected image, so
here's your sort of secret sauce.
You have described the structure of
the raw images folder here, run raw.
And then for the transform,
for the corrected images
you have a run data folder.
Could call it run corrected right?
Raw and data could also be called raw and
corrected.
And you see the correspondence here
in the structure and of course,
you can then use that to
write queries against it.
So somebody has to this, yes.
All right,
I think I want to leave it at that,
that gives you a first idea and
this tool, you're going to be able,
in fact you need to use for
your group project.
So when you model your data cleaning
workflow, you may not have a script
you might just have your overall
workflow but you start with open refine.
And maybe you have a load script
you load it into SQL lite and
then maybe you create some reports.
And maybe you visualise the reports and
then you can write sort of a workflow
model that you can devise a workflow model
that That documents what you've done.
And then you can, again,
ask questions about that.
All right, so
we'll leave it at this for now.
And then next week we continue with
prominence and also continuous
of this demonstration
[MUSIC]