Nalvaravu makkale !!!
In this week's lectures,
we have seen that workflows and provenance are closely related.
Workflows can be seen as a special form of prospective provenance that describes
data flow and data dependencies of
data products in terms of inputs and intermediate steps.
Retrospective provenance can be understood as
traditional trace or logging information where
runtime observables are captured that document the data processing history and lineage.
In the upcoming videos, we will take a closer look at a particular tool for modeling,
visualizing, and querying provenance from script-based workflows.
That is, we will be working with the YesWorkflow tool.