So up to now, we've been using
Datalog was for simple queries,
and you might not
realize that you have
really a power tool at
your fingertips here.
Just to summarize what
is it that we can do,
we can specify integrity
constraints as rules,
and then those rules are also
queries that allow us to
check whether a given database
satisfies these rules.
So we can see for example,
whether a certain column or
a set of columns is a key,
whether a foreign key
is really satisfied.
So whether for every occurrence
of foreign key attributes,
there is a corresponding
occurrence in the parent table.
So this is quite convenient
how we can do this.
We can also do datalog
as a query language
has a built-in mechanism
for recursion.
Why is that useful?
That's useful when you have
data structures that themselves
are trees or graphs,
you can use that query
language as well.
So if you have a question
about a graph or a tree,
you will have a rather hard time
doing that in SQL.
There are some tricks
and some workarounds but
it's rather tedious and
not always possible.
When we use the data
look language we can actually
ask questions about trees
and graphs as well.
So this is something we're
going to do in a future class.
Now, I want to jump into
this topic called
Answer Set Programming.
Again, that's a whole
topic by itself for
a class, logic-based AI class,
but we're going to just look
at the particular application
for automatic repair
of a database,
when a database violates
a certain integrity constraint.
Okay. So we just want to
get a flavor of that,
otherwise it's a rather deep
topic that requires a lot of
additional lectures to
really do full justice.
But we can get
an idea of it so we
know that this technique exists.