[MUSIC]
So we have a student table and we have
functional dependency, so FD not FK.
It was a mistake on the previous slide.
So FD functional dependency,
we want that the ID implies the name.
How would I check that
this is not violated?
So I just put what I call
a soft constraint here.
And I say if I have student X, Y and
another one X, Z but for the same X right
sometimes I've written this in the past a
little bit more laboriously like X1 = X2.
And I can write it just to make it
a little more explicit for a moment.
I say, let me make it really clear.
I think this notation makes it a little
clearer, if I rename the variables.
So what does this rule say?
It says I have two student tuples,
X1, Y1, and X2, Y2, right?
I want it to be the case that X1 = X2,
so they agree on the key but
they shall disagree on the second column.
So the Y1 and the Y2 are different.
That's a situation we don't want to have.
If we have this situation, however, we
want to report this in an auxiliary table
called integrity constraint violation for
dysfunctional dependency.
So, we've seen this before,
so I'll run this again.
And I'm going to just comment out any
other rules that we don't want to get in
our way here.
And then we're going to try this out.
So if you can try this out also
from the command line, on a Mac,
on Windows, on Linux.
I'll do it here inside of this editor
because I find this somewhat convenient,
I'm going to have to save this first.
And I create a new shell, for some reason
it puts it here next to each other.
Hopefully that works
reasonably well as well.
So when I call, the system is called dlv
as you recall, I say repair and maybe I
want to filter a particular relationship I
only want to see maybe the student table.
And I see here that I have
a couple of student tuples.
It's not particularly pretty the way these
tuples are output, but it's all there.
Actually, let me try to do
a horizontal split here.
Yeah, so
you see a little bit more of this, okay?
Now we want to find out who is
violating this integrity constraint and
we should already see this, right?
So how many answers will we get?
Two, for bell and logan, yeah?
So let's look at,
let's filter on this icv_fd relationship.
So 101, bell and logan and logan and bell,
they both share the key 101, which is
a problem, so we need to fix that.
And then stevens and ftevens,
may be that was an OCR error, right?
So may be this was automatically entered
into the database, so stevens and
ftevens may be it should also be stevens.
And that shows also up twice.
So first of all I want to show you, again,
to simplify this rule instead of X1 = X2,
I can just replace X here and
get rid of this X1 = X2.
And again, this X1 here just becomes an X.
I have done a logic transformation.
This is exactly the same rule,
it just looks simpler.
And that's why normally
we would prefer this.
So let's run this again, we get exactly
the same answer, not surprisingly.
All right, so so far so good.
Now if we add another person called ball,
maybe a typo of bell or
just really a different person
who also gets student id 101,
how many violations should I get now?
So somehow we got two until
we got four answers but
there's really two pairs, right,
because we got each pair reported twice.
So how many pairs should I get,
eight, six?
Any other numbers?
So ball with bell, ball with logan,
and bell with logan.
One, two, three pairs.
So six maybe, sixes or four?
Let's see.
All right and since this is hard to count,
instead of saying Y1 not equal to Y2,
we just say less.
We get half of the solutions.
And counting half is,
in this case, a good idea,
because then we can multiply it by 2,
okay?
And to see what we would
have gotten otherwise.
So we got ball and bell, ball and
logan, bell and logan, and
ftevens and,
sorry I forgot the number four guy.
So this guy is destroying our little
calculation, so I'm going to kill Mr.
stevens.
Stevens got to go, right?
So if I kick out stevens, we've got
indeed three pairs that are a problem,
just as expected.
And if we bring back the symmetric
pair the other way around, so
I should get six now, right?
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Three pairs, six double pairs.
Now if I bring back Mr.
stevens, or rather ftevens,
how's that going to affect things?
Then we're going to get another two,
right?
And here is I think the eighth.
So six and eight were both right in a way,
depending on whether you
counted stevens or not.
Okay great, so
we got lots of violations here.
So how can we fix things here?
Let me first get rid of Mr. ftevens here
and also let me get rid of maybe logan.
We got still a violation, right?
We still got one pair.
Bell and ball.
There's something with them.
And now what we want to do is we want to,
okay, before I go to the repair,
I want to just give one example
how these logic systems,
this answer set programming
system normally is used.
Here we're using the system
to check violations, but
then we don't reject the answer.
We kind of try to do something with it,
like deleting one of the bad guys, right?
Something like that.
When we use a system like this in
a logic setting as a constraint solver,
we actually don't work
with soft constraints,
which are really just queries that
give us answers of problematic tuples.
But instead,
we kind of kill the whole model.
We say, no, if there's an inconsistency,
don't even show me the thing.
I just want to point this out,
what this is.
This is called a hard constraint.
So when you have nothing in the head, or
you can think of it as having
false in the head, this says,
if I have an integrity constraint
violation, whatsoever, I want to stop.
Just don't show me that.
And instead of false,
I write literally nothing there.
This is sort of a very subtle syntax
if I did the little not insidious,
but there's a lot of power
behind this little rule.
And you have to know that this is what
it's doing to see what's happening.
So this is basically saying if there's
any integrity constraint validation,
I will not report anything.
So if I run this program now, you see,
even if I switch off the filter,
there's no answer.
This says the set of rules that
you've given to me are inconsistent.
There is a contradiction.
So this is a useful feature when you
have lots of possibilities, thousands or
maybe millions of combinations and
you want to kill off those
that make the system inconsistent and
only report on the consistent ones.
Here we're sort of using
a variation of the theme.
We don't use these hard constraints.
We use the soft constraints to
report on the bad guys and then
try out some repair actions and then let
the system report on those repair actions.
So that's a subtle difference
I wanted to point out.
So if we want to, ourself,
fix the database by say,
well, bell was wrong, it's ball.
And ftevens is wrong, it's stevens.
Now the database should be consistent.
And if I run this repair example, it will
tell us there's these three students,
it's all good.
But once we introduce an inconsistency,
never mind which ones, stevens and
ftevens, there's no answer.
So this is of course
a rather drastic measure.
Again, there are applications
where this is useful.
For our purposes, this is too drastic.
So we don't want to think of
this hard constraint saying,
if there is a violation, abort.
No, that's not what we want to do.
We say, okay fine,
we're not going to use that.
Instead, if there's a violation,
let's report on the violation.
And now let's try and
do something about it.
And that again is the idea of the repair.
What are we going to do about it is rather
simple and this is where the system is so
powerful that you can just
write down the following rule.
It says,
if there's an integrity violation and
let's use this new notation with Y1 and
Y2.
If you rename things, clearly that doesn't
change the meaning of a rule, right?
Renaming variables in your Java program
doesn't change the Java program,
it might change the readability.
Similar here in logic, if I rename
the variables in a consistent manner,
it helps the readability
along a little bit.
So here we have a rule that is a little
bit unusual from the rules we've
seen so far.
It has a body, which is a query, but
then in the head there's
something really strange going on.
There's this funny or symbol, and
again normal systems, normal data lock
systems will not give you that power.
Here, it just says, well, if I have two
values, Y1 and Y2, I don't have to check
that they are different, why don't I
have to check that they are different?
Because they only got in there if
they were different to begin with.
So I know Y1 and Y2 are different,
I could possibly write it there again,
but at this point it's not really needed.
So they only got in there if Y1 and
Y2 are different.
This is clearly a violation, so
one of the two has to go, so
this is what I write here.
So maybe let's run this program and
see what's going to happen.
The hard constraint,
if I had both, if I had this and
that together that basically,
these are not really kind of alternatives.
What's happening is this one collects
the integrity constraint violations
in an auxiliary table,
auxiliary relation, if you like.
And this one acts upon it.
Only that the action of killing off
the model is a little drastic for
our purposes.
Again in sort of AI settings or
where we use this to generate answers and
then filter out the ones that work,
this is the way to go, it's not for us.
So here, we literally switch it off but
we collect the integrity constraint
violators and then we offer to
delete one of the violators.
And let's have a look here.
Right now, let's bring stevens
here out of the picture and
look just at bell and ball.
What should we see?
What do you think
the answer will look like?
So I have a violation between ball and
bell.
Everything else is okay.
The violation will be
reported kind of both ways.
And then this rule will say,
well, if I have a violation,
then I should either delete this guy or
that guy.
So what do you think we
should see when we run this?
Well, let's try it out.
That's the beauty of it.
Aha, so we get somehow two answers.
Let's just filter on
the student deletion table,
to really zoom in on what's going on.
So there are two answers,
one says, you gotta delete bell, then
the word's okay, or you gotta delete ball.
But notice there is this
sort of two separate lines.
It's really two separate worlds.
In fact I can count the possible worlds
as we'll show in a moment using certain
trick.
Does it delete randomly?
No, the answer is right now this is
just an auxiliary table that we've
created to identify the candidates,
the deletion candidates.
And nobody has been deleted so
far at this point.
When I have ball and bell and
logan, all sharing the same id,
then we can either delete ball and
bell, logan wins, or ball and
logan, bell wins or
bell and logan, ball wins.
Now that's of course is
a little bit complicated and
tedious to keep track of
all these combinations.
So what we should do is we should execute
the deletion by computing a new table.
Whoever we deleted is no longer there.
So how do we do this?
So we create a new students table,
I call it new student.
And it has an interesting
body of the rule.
It says, well take any student X,
Y that you have and
as long as they're not deleted,
they'll make it into the next round.
It's a little bit like what is it?
Survivor or getting into the next round.
Not getting voted off the island,
that's what's happening here.
So whoever's been deleted, will not
make it into the new student table.
What we should see now instead of,
in this case,
these three alternative variants
of what needs to be deleted.
You see in each of these three variants,
two guys need be deleted but one survives,
who survives?
That should be now in the new student
table, should be a little easier to see.
So we run the program again, and
instead of looking a the deleted students,
we just look at who is there after
getting voted off the island, okay?
If you look at,
it's sort of little bit backwards but
you see 101 is either logan, bell or ball.
And stevens and norton are untouched,
so there are three possible worlds.
I can actually count the possible
worlds if I pipe this into word count,
which is a tool that's available
on Unix based systems.
It'll tell us, so this vertical symbol
is a pipe, whatever the output from
the previous program is sent into this
word count program, the word count program
tells us there are 7 lines in the answer,
22 words and 301 characters.
But the number of lines is for
us, an indication.
Now something is a little wrong here,
because we've one line here,
second, third, four, five,
six, seven, seven lines.
But only three of these seven
lines are meaningful and
four lines are kind of useless.
So there is an option called silent,
command line option.
When I run silent,
it will just give me one answer per line.
And if I count them now,
this is very convenient,
now I see there are three
different solutions.
For three, it's easy to see, for
10,000, it's harder to count.
So that's a useful trick here.
This will work on your Unix
based system or a Mac or
it will work on a Windows based system,
if you use a bash or
similar sort of Unix type shell,
then you'll get the benefits here as well.
So let's try to make a little prediction
and then we'll take a little break.
Let's try to make a little prediction and
see what's going to happen.
We have three different kinds of repairs.
If I switch off the word count,
I see the three repairs.
They all have to do with 101.
Instead of filtering on new student,
I can also look at the delete.
Now what was that delete student
relationship, so they all go together.
Let's have a look.
So if you look at each line separately.
Actually here I can
switch off the silent to
give us an empty line between the answers.
This makes it little easier to read.
So again,
we see the same what we saw before.
Stevens and norton always make it because
there's no problem with their id,
but there's sort of
a contention about the id 101.
And either you delete ball and bell and
you keep logan, or you delete ball and
logan and you keep bell, or you delete
bell and logan and you keep ball, okay?
So you see, it's all these combinations,
it'll all make some sense, you delete two,
you keep the third.
So each world, what is called a possible
world in the terminology of this
approach or each answer set.
That's why it's called
answer set programming.
There's three answer sets.
Each world corresponds to one answer set.
And so each answer set gives you one
consistent way how you can repair.
And if you think about what we've done,
this was pretty straight forward.
We had an integrity constraint
that we could check.
We can come up with any
integrity constraint really.
And the meta approach, the Uber approach
if you like to this is, we'll just invent
some rules to tell you, in case of a
violation, what is it that you want to do?
So that's what we've done here.
We said well, if I have a violation,
we'll delete one or delete the other.
If you have more complicated situations,
you can do other things as well.
But the key to the power of this approach
is that we generate different possible
answers with the or, and
then the system sort of figures out which
of these various answers work together.
And in this particular case we said, okay,
we need the final step where we say in
the new state, the repaired state, we take
a copy of what was previously the case and
then we execute in a way the action.
Or we filter out, in this case,
the tuples that should be deleted,
we don't let them go into the next state.
So, again, it's a simple example,
but a lot is going on.
And if you generalize that,
that's behind all of these or most of
these repair approaches in databases.
So the foundations of it, I think,
we got pretty much worked out.
We have a database, in this case,
a very simple constraint,
which is a functional dependency.
And then we have a generation
of possible repairs.
And then we have an execution
of these repairs.
How is it chosen which
student is to be deleted?
Well, the answer is it's systematically
enumerating all possible repairs.
It's choosing by looking at all of them,
trying to be fair.
That's why we have three answers here.
A real database system, sometimes you are
stuck because you have to make a decision.
You have to decide which of these three
possible worlds do I want to have.
In a more complex situation, you might
have other rules that point out, well,
just this bell guy show up somewhere
else in the database in another table.
Or does logan or ball show up somewhere?
Or if something shows up in
a dictionary as a valid name and
the ftevens probably doesn't show up
in a dictionary, that's not a name.
And then more comprehensive solution,
you will probably want to post process
your choices, and then rank them somehow.
Before I break,
let me just do, just to see a sort of
a multiplication effect here that occurs.
So you see ball, bell and
logan were three possible worlds.
And now I'm going to say stevens and
ftevens are also ending up in
the database,
maybe a transcription error for 104.
How many possible worlds
do you think we get now?
So one idea could be let's
see what happens if we
get rid of the problem with the 101s.
Let's just say ball is the guy,
then for stevens, right,
we should get two different worlds.
Either we delete ftevens and
we keep stevens or
we delete stevens and we keep ftevens.
In this particular case,
if I bring back the other three choices,
those are independent.
Sometimes they might actually
interact in complex ways.
That's where the power of the system lies,
that it can keep also track of maybe
one of the solutions, interact somehow,
correlate with the other ones.
In this case, they're really independent.
So I think we will get three times two.
Let's try it out, okay?
Well now we have to start counting or
we use our trick from before.
First of all, we use this silent
option to get rid of the white space,
the extra lines.
And then we pipe it into
tool called word count, and
it tells us there are six worlds.
[MUSIC]