Welcome back.
Now let's wrap up what we have learned about
the data log queries and integrity constraints this week.
In our overall data cleaning workflow,
we have arrived at the logical or semantic level,
where we use logic-based integrity constraints to check the consistency of data.
We have seen how to express integrity constraints as
special data look rules in denial form.
These senile queries can be used to identify the troublemakers, that is,
the parts of the data that is implicated in a consistency violation.
We also briefly looked at recursive queries and data log.
In upcoming lectures, we will then revisit the topic of recursive queries,
for example, when querying provenance graphs.
Before doing so, however,
we will first transfer our new skills from data log to SQL.
This will be the topic next week.