[MUSIC]
Hello, and welcome back to Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
In this last series of videos, we will
look at the very specific data quality
issue, that is the use of
multiple vocabularies.
At the beginning of this course,
we saw that different spellings of names
or places can lead to poor data quality.
Our remedy was to transform, for example,
using open refine, those different
spellings into a set of canonical names,
or a controlled vocabulary.
So clearly,
the use of a controlled, as opposed to
a wild variety, can improve data quality.
There are applications areas where the use
of controlled vocabularies is widespread
and well established.
For example, the National Library of
Medicine has developed many controlled
vocabularies for the Biomedical Sciences.
The so called
Unified Medical Language System or UMLS.
It provides a mapping structure
among those vocabularies.
And thus, allows one to translate
among the various terminology systems.
It may also be viewed as
a comprehensive thesaurus and
ontology of biomedical concepts and can
be used for natural language processing.
Similarly, biodiversity informatics
researchers use controlled vocabularies,
in particular,
hierarchical structures called taxonomies
to organize the different
Kingdoms of Life.
For example, plants,
animals, fungi, and so on.
In all these cases, the use of controlled
vocabularies is beneficial and often
essential in order to conduct meaningful
data analysis and scientific studies.
But what do you do when data
coming from different sources or
different times,
maybe historical data from 100 years ago,
comes annotated with different
controlled vocabularies or taxonomies?
[MUSIC]