[సంగీతం]
Hello and welcome back to Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
Last week we looked at
the relational data model and
provided a brief introduction
to relational queries.
This week we will continue our work with
the relational model and delve further
into relational queries and integrity
constraints, specifically in Datalog.
Now that we have left syntax and pattern
based data quality issues behind us,
the key idea going forward is to operate
at the logical or semantic level.
Now dirty data means
logically inconsistent data.
And we will use relational queries to
check whether integrity constraints
are satisfied or not.
Specifically we will write
queries in denial form,
that is in a form that describes the bad
situations that we want to avoid.
First we will look at common
relational constraints,
that is, functional dependencies or
key constraints as they're also called.
And inclusion dependencies, for example,
foreign keys in relational
databases are a special case.
While these constraints can be
understood as formulas in first order
predicate logic.
It is much more convenient and
practical to write them down in
the form of executable Datalog rules.
Datalog rules consist of a head
to the left-hand side and
a body to the right-hand side.
And we can think of it as follows,
the body of a rule specifies various
query conditions and is evaluated first.
Then, for those variable
bindings that satisfy the body or
right-hand side of the rule, the head or
left-hand side can be asserted.
That is, new answers are generated.
After having worked through
this week's materials and
the associated assignment, you should be
able to formulate and execute queries and
integrity constraints in Datalog.
You will also be able to recognize and
deal with common Datalog pitfalls, for
example rules that are not safe.
For a rule to be safe,
every variable must occur positively
at least once in the body.
In other words, if a variable only
occurs in the head of the rule or
only negatively in the body then we
cannot limit this variable's range.
That is we cannot enumerate
its possible values and
the Datalog system will report an error.
In the assignment you will practice how to
write simple relational queries in Datalog
and how to express logical
integrity constraints as Datalog
queries in denial form.
Learning a bit of Datalog allows you to
see more directly the underlying logic
patterns used to express and
check relational data integrity.
In subsequent lectures we will then
also go more mainstream by employing
SQL queries for
similar integrity constraint checks.
While highly relevant in practice, a skill
sometimes obscures the underlying logical
kernel of queries and
integrity constraints.
Which is why we look at Datalog first.
Okay, let's jump right
into the first lecture.
[సంగీతం]
[SOUND]