موسيقى
Welcome back, now let's wrap up what we
have learned about the relational model
and queries this week.
We have seen that the relational data
model is based on tables that have
a regular structure called
the schema of a relation.
A number of different query languages
have been devised for relational data.
The common foundation underlying
relational query languages,
is first order predicate logic.
What we have used here
it's more user friendly,
rule-based cousin called Datalog.
In the assignment,
you will write simple Datalog queries and
logical integrity constraints
to identify data quality issues,
that can spend multiple columns or tables.
Datalog is not only helpful in
understanding the logical foundations of
queries and integrity constraints, but
it is also used in the real world for
specialized applications.
For example the cursive
querying of graph and
network data and
in online analytical processing.
In subsequent lectures, we will then
look even closer at integrity constraint
checking in the relational model, and
we will use not only Datalog but also SQL.
موسيقى