[MUSIC]
Hello and welcome back to theory and
practice of data cleaning.
In previous videos, we have introduced
workflows as a means to automate data
cleaning and analysis pipelines.
We have also taken a first
look at workflows as a form of
prospective provenance.
That describes the data flow or
recipe by which input data moves through
a workflow while being transformed.
And giving rise to intermediate and
final data outputs.
In these week's videos,
we will take a closer look at provenance.
Provenance describes the origin and
history of artifacts.
Provenance also plays a prominent
role in the national sciences.
Where researchers are trying
to understand the world and
the present by looking at the past.
For example, biologists study
the natural history of life on earth and
specifically the phylogeny or
tree of life of organisms.
In astronomy or astrophysics,
provenance questions are studied
in an area called cosmology.
Closer from home, we may study the
geneology that is our family history or
someone's academic pedigree,
that is the tree of academic ancestors.
In languages we study etymology, that is
the origin of words and their meanings.
In the computational and data sciences,
we are interested, of course,
in the computational provenance of data.
For example, to guarantee transparency and
reproducibility of our methods.
And to allow others to inspect
the quality of the processes that lead
to the result data.
As opposed to looking
only at the end product,
that is only a data quality itself.
In upcoming videos we will
also look at example tools and
projects in which provenance
is prominently used.
For this we will learn about the workflow
tool and the DataONE project,
respectively.
Okay, let's get started with
our lectures on provenance.
[MUSIC]