Let's go back to some finer
points of the W3C Prov model.
If you zoom in to the standard you will
then find that what we call entity,
or in our case, data itself can
be made up of different things.
This could be a collection, so
that could be nested data, often data
is structured into nested collections.
There's something called a bundle and
something called a plan.
This is a part of
the standard that I somewhat
think of it as slightly confusing.
A plan is really more a work flow thing.
But it is, in this case,
associated with an entity.
There's some method to this scheme,
but to the beginner,
this might look a little bit confusing.
And there's also different
relationships between entities.
So we've seen before, there is
the wasDerivedFrom relationship, but
there's also now variations of
what's influenced by Was quote from,
was a revision of, or had primary source.
So there's a little vocabulary of
relationships when you say this data was
derived from this other data it
could mean different things.
So the standard has further
refinements of that.
And then again agents who are agents.
This could be a software agent as
I mentioned before, a process.
Or it could be a person
maybe even an organization.
And as standards go,
they have to also describe or
prescribe what formats are used for
exchange of data in the standard, so
you see some things like there's a date,
time.
So this XML schema Standard for
that as well.
Now let me zoom out.
It is easy to get lost in these standards
with all their technical details.
So I just want to put
things again back into
context before I continue
here with the material.
So I want to talk about
provenance as it shows up.
In the most general setting,
namely in science.
If you think about it, there's all these
different notions of provenance
that really scientists care about.
Cosmologists, for example,
they ask very far-reaching questions,
literally far-reaching questions.
They study the origin of the universe or
the cosmos.
Biologists study the origin of life.
Phylogeny's here ,you see
a little thumbnail there.
If you're into genealogy, you want to
know where your family came from and
what are the relationships,
again, you look back in history.
There's also something
called an academic pedigree,
which is sort of your academic ancestors.
So if you have, for example,
a PhD in the mathematical sciences or
computer science, there's a nice
online database where you can look up
whether you through your advisor
are connected to some famous people.
Maybe it makes you feel better about
your own academic history that way.
Etymology of course is the study
of origin, where words come from.
So earlier chain of custody
in the case of artifacts.
And so
all of these different uses of provenance,
they really use provenance to
understand The present, right?
We use the past, we use the history
to understand the present better.
And so this is also our connection to why
we study provenance in the context of
data quality and science and
scientific reproducibility.
The connection is if you
have a data artifact or
rather a knowledge artifact in this case,
like this plot on the right hand side.
You can say this clearly shows
that temperatures were have
been rising recently, yeah?
So there's on the y axis,
you see a temperature scale.
It's in Centigrades, Celsius.
And on the x axis you see years.
And well, what do all these things mean?
How did I arrive at this curve?
Is this really something significant?
How much can I trust this?
This is why,
in particular in climate science but
really in all sciences,
this topic of reproducibility is central.
It's not science unless somebody
else can reproduce what I have.
And in data science in particular Of
course, the point is if we output or
put forward analysis results, we need to
document how we arrived at those results.
We need to show the input data,
intermediate data.
We need to show the quote,
we need to document all methods.
And this is where provenance
comes into the picture.
So for scientist to be transparent and
reproducible about what they're doing,
we need to know these questions
that I have here on the slide.
What input data went into the study?
What methods were used?
What were the particular
parameter settings?
What were the calibrations used?
So we want to know whether we can
trust the data and the methods.
And again,
since Provenance is the lineage of data
we want to track the origin where the data
came from and the processing history.
What tools were used to analyze the data?
And then there's also
other uses of provenance.
The primary use of
provenance is really for
transparency and its broader context for
reproducibility.
But then also you can discover,
for example,
data and methods used on that provenance.
I mean, at some point, provenance becomes
data itself, and you can index it,
you can search based on provenance,
and so on.
So let me show you some more
examples Of that before we move on.
So again this is climate change,
a hot topic these days.
And there was an online
database developed,
GCIS, Global Change Information System.
And it has plots like the one here.
And metadata that's indicated.
So let me zoom into this a little bit.
Here's an example from the Texas Summer
2011, a record heat and drought.
And the data visualized
in the upper right is described
through metadata that's on the left.
For example, we have a bounding box.
We see this dataset is about
this region of the US.
So there's this bounding box,
the blue box that you see there.
And then there's these relationships
that we just talked about,
provenance that say well,
how was this dataset created?
So this dataset was derived from
another dataset Using an activity,
using a process, or using a script.
So if you were to zoom in here,
you'd get these problems records as part
of this online database or
information system.
So you can look at this Provenance
information just on the screen as HTML.
But there's also a sort of
a machine-readable format.
So if you click on one
of these buttons below.
You can get this same provenance
information in JSON, in XML, Turtle,
Triple syntax, all kinds of various
syntaxes that would allow you to
write now queries or
other analysis on the provenance itself.
So promised data becomes data itself,
a promised information becomes data
itself that you can analyze in query.
So this kind of state-of-the-art
here in provenance,
when you do science, this report,
the Climate Change Impacts in the US,
was a very large effort to document
how change in climate affects the US.
And what was done, this information
system that's online here,
is really to support
the findings of that report.
And again, to support the findings
themselves is provenance information,
to increase the trust it that.
But creating provenance
information is still tedious and
a large effort Which is why some projects,
for example DataOne mentioned here,
creates products and tools that support
the creation of provenance in an easy way.
As you conduct your scientific study,
wouldn't it be nice if the provenance
information already was produced
as a side effect of your work.
So it's not an afterthought
that later you have to kind of
explain yourself after what you've done.
But it would be nice that as you do your
science and in this case as you do your
data science, or computational science,
if at that time province is captured.
And then you can use it for
your own purposes as well.
If you have Issues about data quality, you
can look at the Provenance information and
find out what has happened and
maybe redo some of your experiments.
All right, I don't want to say too
much about DataONE other than it's
a federally funded large project,
so NSF funded.
There's a website,
you can go there, DataONE.org, and
in particular, there's a search
interface called search DataONE.org.
And just very briefly, what it is, it's
really a federation of data repositories.
It consists of so-called
coordinating nodes.
You can think of them almost as the
brokers between other data repositories.
The data repositories that
exist are called member nodes.
So it's really a network of
existing data repositories.
And then that's often associated
in investigative tool kit.
So these are, in addition to the website,
there are tools that allow you to work
with the data from those member nodes.
Now I want to just finally make
that connection to provenance.
So when you have identified the data
that you want to work with,
some of the data, and hopefully
increasingly more of the data comes with
provenance information attached.
And on the website, you would see for
any dataset that you found using a search
functionality, you might find this little,
the thing that looks like a pitch fork.
Yeah, it is really an icon
meant to indicate that
this data that has provenance with it.
So this is saying,
here I have a data set but
I can also tell you how
I got this data set.
How was it computed?
How was it derived?
So this is a little bit highlighted there,
how that works and
if you then unpack all of that you
might get the full on picture.
You might see that maybe the plots
that you see in the lower right
have been created using scripts and
other data set and
that this difference of snapshots that are
stacked up there indicate how the output
plots were created from input data sets
and scripts and how they connect together.
And the thing we see in the middle is
a particular tool called Yes Book Flow
that has created this diagram.
This is as tool to present scientific
analysis that was conducted using a script
saying Map Lab or
in this case as in R or in Python.
If you have such a workflow
that's implemented as a script,
you do want to also document.
What other main steps?
What is the the data flow in the script.
What other main artifacts that
the script produces and consumes?
It's important to document that and
this is a simple way to do so.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]