[MUSIC]
I'm going to talk about YesWorkflow.
We're going to move toward YesWorkflow
which is a system and tool for
provinence for script based workflows.
So when we have scripts instead
of a proper work flow system
how can we provide some of the benefits
of scientific workflow systems
to those people who have scripts,
and there are many of those.
So I'm going to talk about that.
But first, why are we interested in that?
Well, if you think about what workflow
tools most scientists are using,
there are a number that
use workflow systems.
But it's often in sort
of specialized domains.
And if you look at how many people
are using Python and R and MATLAB and
similar scripting languages, for
workflow-like activities for automation of
say, computational science, and
data science, and analysis pipelines.
You'll see that the customer base for
the script based approach is very large
much larger than for workflow systems.
Also what provenance tools exist?
Well again the workflow systems themselves
often have very nice provenance support.
The workflow itself is a kind of
provenance if you want to think about
it this way.
Then the workflow system allow
you to record data lineage, but
what about people who write
their workflow as scripts?
There is not so much out there.
I'll give you an example,
from one of our own projects.
This is a research project funded again
by the National Science Foundation
called SKOPE.
It stands for Synthesized Knowledge
of Past Environments.
And he would be an example from
a publication, in this case in nature
communications by two scientists and
collaborators Bocinsky and Kohler.
And they have a paper on the 2000
year reconstruction of rain fed maze
agricultural nitch in
the United States Southwest.
So this is about the southwestern
states in the U.S..
And they create this wonderful
climate models that kind of explain
retro-actively or try to retrodict
the climate from 1,000 to 2,000 years ago.
What do they use to do that?
So they create these nice models and
they create these nice graphs.
But what are the tools that they use?
They use tools that are very
well suited for the job,
something that works very well,
and that's R.
And R is of course available for
free and it's an open source
system and a lot of scientists use it to
publish their own studies as open source.
So here you have an R script that
kind of goes together with the paper.
Goes together with the dataset, but how
can your really document the big picture?
What is the method?
Of course you should read the paper.
The paper explains what
the method is very well.
But are there some additional artifacts
that you could consider look at?
To really assess is this a method I
want to use maybe for my studies.
And if you want to have a first idea about
what are the characteristic features of
this method.
Again, you can look at the paper and
then you can look at the code.
What we're aiming here however is
something in between a conceptual
level data flow diagram that
is the equivalent of what you
would see if you had used the workflow
system instead of using R.
So this is the goal.
So again here, we're looking at a use
case paleoclimate reconstruction.
Here is another paper by
the same co-authors here.
This one published in Science Advances.
Again, it uses open source code.
So these scientists do the right
thing here they publish
their methods openly using code
in open source repository.
But how do I understand what
exactly the method entails?
What are the data artifacts that go in and
out?
Is there something I can do other than
looking at the code to get a high level
conceptual view.
And there's also things that really
aren't really embedded in the code.
Certain dependencies are not easily, or
maybe not at all
extractable from the code.
And so we want to end up with a diagram
like we see here on the right.
Where you have data going into a workflow
and then there's computational steps and
phases and data products popping out, and
you want to know how
that all works together.
And so the tool that we've been developing
in my group is called YesWorkflow.
You can think of it as sort of
a recognition of the fact that yes,
scripts are workflows too.
Or at least scripts can be workflows too.
Not every script is a workflow.
But often times a script can be
a workflow in that it automates certain
repetitive tasks or it describes
really a computational pipeline.
If you compare a script to some
of the characteristic features of
a workflow system, you see it gets its
job done of automation quite well.
When it comes to scaling, that's maybe
a little more difficult if you use
a certain library together with your code,
you can then maybe paralyze your code.
So there's some support for that but
still requires a lot of additional effort.
But abstraction is really I think the main
thing where scripts somewhat fall short.
They're fine for the author who wrote
them, but they're kind of hard to extract
the sort of more high level conceptual
view of what the script is doing.
Again, what are the inputs?
What are the outputs?
What are the intermediate steps?
What are the intermediate products?
So this where we really
want to make a contribution.
And then in terms of Provenance support,
again scripts can actually
record their own Provenance.
Maybe user writes a log file that
documents what the script is doing.
Maybe you have a generic library that
writes, that records, intercepts,
maybe read and write operations and
kind of traces what's going on.
So there is such support also.
So it's a little bit better than, I think,
their support for abstraction and
workflow models but
it is still somewhat limited.
So this is where the motivation
comes from for the YesWorkflow tool.
We would like to go from scripts
somehow to workflow diagram that tells
us something about
the processing history and
the data lineage of data that pops out at
the end of such script based workflow.
So let me jump right in and show you
some examples here how that is done.
And there's an associated
reading as usual.
So here is a snippet of code.
In this case, this is Python code.
And in order to use that YesWorkflow
approach, what the user has to do,
or the author, it should be really
the author of the script who knows best
what the script is doing.
There should be some declarations
embedded in the script.
And they are not meant to document
exactly what the code is doing.
Because what the code is doing there's
already coding comments in there.
It's really more about describing
the things that are not in the code or
at least not obvious from the code or
not even at all in the code.
And what is that?
If you think of a problem standard, we
heard that there are these Activities or
how we would like to call
them according to the OPM
model the previous standard processes.
What other processes.
We think of them as steps.
I like to use sort of
a somewhat more generic term
What are the computational
steps of my methods?
And we're going to look at this
in more detail, but basically
you just declare a step by saying here's
the beginning, here's the end of the step.
Typically, you would embed
this in the code because you
get the additional
benefit that you can then
connect your conceptual model with
the code right there in one place.
But you might as well create that model.
Outside of your script.
You might do it on a piece of paper or
in a separate file that is somehow
separate from the script itself.
Or maybe you don't have
the script quite yet.
And so you can create these workflow
models in the simple annotation
language inside of the code.
As embedded comments or
outside of the code if you prefer.
And the basic mechanism by which
you define this is you say,
here is a code block or here is a step,
really that here's the beginning and end.
So you just declare the step, and then
you just basically say what goes in and
out of the step.
So in the end it's rather simple.
You just say This is a step and
this goes in and this goes out.
And by wiring this together
the workflow diagram is obtained.
So here's an example of the right and
we're going to look at some of this
more closely of such a work flow.
The green boxes indicate steps,
again the providence models you
would think of this as a process.
Maybe even an activity, but for
our purposes, it's a computational step.
It's a method somehow, and
a data transformation step,
maybe a data cleaning step.
And then the more yellowish nodes
are the data that flows between the steps.
And you can easily imagine that
it's not terrible difficult
to create these diagrams You basically
have to say what are those boxes and
how do they connect to one another?
And the simple way again to do this is
to declare the green boxes as saying
here's such a green box, here's a step.
And then you say what goes in and
out of the step.
And then we use an external
tool called graph base.
That gives us a nice layout, so we don't
have to worry about the visualization.
We outsource that to another tool.
And what does this give you if you have,
like in this case,
spent maybe half an hour
on marking up your script?
Once you get the hang of it,
it shouldn't take all that long.
Well, I should say there's
also modeling freedom.
May be something that's
sometimes underestimated.
Maybe you don't need a complex
workflow diagram like that.
Maybe you do one big green box that says,
this is what my method does.
It's one box, I call it my method,
maybe poly OCR or clean this, or
whatever is your application.
And then you just declare the inputs and
outputs, and you're done.
Yeah, that's maybe a starting point.
Well you say, you know what?
I think i really need to reveal
what's going on inside of the box.
And then, this is an example of the
diagram that you see here in the right.
Here, we've opened up the box, and
we can see that it consist of multiple
steps that are connected in a certain way.
Once you've spent the effort of Doing
this additional what feels like
maybe a metadata chore, but you do
get some value out of it immediately.
First of all, you can create
different views on top of that.
So you model this once, and
then you can tell the tool, and
say, I would like to see just the steps.
Just give me the steps.
Is it even more abstract
view of the diagram,
just let's not get lost in the data.
Or you can say no wait a minute,
I'm really interested in data
let's not show the steps,
let's just connect the data.
So this is in some sense similar
to the west derived relationship
that we had in the promise standard.
Only that this is, at this point,
still a workflow model.
This is not retrospective providence.
We have not recorded any
actual execution yet.
This is something that we've sort
of declared or made known upfront.
This is how our method works.
And then of course,
we can have the combined view,
which I think of as the default view for
YesWorkflow models.
You've marked up your
script if you have one or
you've just created this
model using annotations.
So you're having these boxes
that stand for steps and
you have data that flows
between the steps.
So again you get all of these
three different models for
free once you've modeled
the one on bottom basically.
So that the one on the top,
that the first two become free.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]