[MUSIC]
Hello, and welcome back to Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
In previous lectures, we looked at the
relational model, and we saw how we can
use relational queries in an elegant
rule language called data log.
We also use data log rules for
checking data integrity.
It is we use so called denial constraints
to detect and report integrity violations.
In the following lectures we will move to
most widely used query language of all
which is SQL.
In this course we will
use an easy to install,
lightweight database engine called
SQLite, for our exercises.
SQLite is particularly popular for
embedded devices.
For example, running right now in
your smart phone, your game consoles,
smart TV, car, web browser, you name it.
Because SQLite requires no server
administration unlike databases used for
multi-user applications.
It is also an ideal tool for the data
scientist who needs to integrity checking,
data profiling and querying and
even some basic data analytics itself.
In the next lectures, I will give
an introduction to SQLite and then a brief
crash course to SQLite using some
publicly available data sets inquiries.
After working through
this week's materials and
the associated assignment,
you should be able to formulate and
execute simple queries and
integrity constraints in SQL.
Some of the examples in
the assignment will look familiar and
this is no accident.
You will be able to see how the integrity
constraints we used earlier in data log
can be formulated also in SQL.
Okay, let's jump right
into the first lecture.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]