Hello, everyone, welcome back.
In this video,
we're going to talk about the other two
Euler problems that were on your handout.
Euler problem 3 is basically find
a largest prime factor of a number.
To do this, we're going to write something
that is kind of like the famous sieve.
Really, not quite as sophisticated as
the real sieve, but it's easy to write.
So we'll do it this way.
In the meantime,
I'm going to show you a few more
features of Haskell as we do this.
Now one thing that we can do is
we can write a function plus.
It just adds its two arguments together.
And if you ask for the type, you'll see
that it gives you back a, arrow, a, arrow,
a, with the constraint that
a must be a numeric thing.
Now, there are two ways that
you can read this type.
The first is you can think of it as
a function that takes two arguments and
then returns a result.
So you see I call plus on 10 and
20 and get 30 back.
But the other way you can look at it is
if you only give plus 1 of its arguments.
Then it's going to
return another function.
So if I call plus 1 and look for the type,
that 1 goes into the first a in the type.
And then you get an a or a back.
So you get another function back.
And when a function is written this
way it's called a curried function.
And we'll have occasion to talk about
this a little bit more in a future video.
But as you see what we can do
is I can call plus on 2, so
that's partially applied.
And then save that into
another function like addTwo.
This is a very common
technique used in Haskell.
The way we're going to make use of this
is we're going to have a function called
notDivides that we can use to filter out
all the things that aren't divisible by
a certain number.
And this is how we're going to
be able to build up our primes.
So you see if I call filter notDivides
3 on the list 1 through 10,
then it's throwing out all
the multiples of 3 for us.
So in order to build up a list,
we're going to need some more syntax.
Now you saw on the previous video,
we could use the square brackets and
just write in all the elements.
But here we're going to have to build
it up a little bit more piece meal.
So what we're going to do
is use this colon notation.
Now if you use the language with linked
lists and singly linked lists, a lot of
times an object joined to language,
you can say stuff like a new Node (a,b).
And a is going to be the data element and
b is going to be a pointer
to another linked list.
And that way you can build
things up incrementally.
So Haskell we have this colon which
does basically the same thing.
So you can see here on line 1,
the 2 is going to be the data element.
And then colon and then filter is
supposed to return another linked list.
And so what this is going to do is create
a new linked list node where the 2 starts
at the beginning and then the rest
of the list comes afterwards.
So the way we're going to
build up our list of primes.
So we'll start with a 2 and
then we'll filter out all the multiples
of 2 from the rest of the list.
And we can stack this up, we can
have a 3 and then filter out the 3s.
Then 5 and filter out the multiples of 5,
so on and so forth.
Of course we're going to want to write
a recursive function to do this for us.
Here's what our sieve
function's going to look like.
And this is going to also show you
two other features of Haskell.
So feature number one, you'll see sieve,
the parameter list is actually the same
syntax for building up a list, the x:xs.
And this is called pattern matching.
So what happens,
if I call sieve and pass it a list,
the first element of the list
is going to get assigned to x.
And the rest of the elements
are going to be assigned to xs.
This is a very nice notation.
It’s very concise.
And you’ll see this used very,
very frequently in this language.
Now the other thing you may notice is
that sieve, there is no base case.
I haven’t written something for
the empty list.
And so this looks like it’s actually
going to build an infinitely large list if
you tried to type this out.
So I say primes = sieve [2..].
If you actually type out primes at
this point, then it won't stop,
it'll keep looping.
But Haskell has another feature,
it's called a lazy evaluation.
So when you write down something, unless
it's actually used in another computation,
Haskell won't actually do
anything with it at all.
It won't perform the computation
until it is actually necessary.
So the way we can make use of that is
we can write down our list of primes.
And we don't have to know how many we
want up front, but we can decide later.
There's a function called take
which will go through and
take the first 20 elements of the list in
this case and return them in a new list.
So these are our primes.
Now that we have that,
we just need to figure out how to
use that to get our largest factor.
So here, to get all the factors,
we're going to take an auxiliary function.
So I want the factors of n.
I'm going to make
an auxiliary function aux.
Then the first element of aux is going to
be the number we're trying to factor.
And if we get down to 1 then we're done.
So we'll return an empty list.
That's what that brackets
with nothing in looks like.
Otherwise, what we're going to do is we're
going to assume that the second argument
to aux is our list of primes.
And we're just going to
through them each one,
we'll just check if p divides into n or
not.
So if it does, then we're going to return
it, and then call aux recursively.
Otherwise, the second case on line 5,
those two underscores mean that
we don't actually want to
assign a variable name to it.
We'll just keep checking
to see what divides out.
And finally, there's a function foldr,
which we're going to take max and
we're going to repeatedly call max
on the elements of this list and
fold them together.
There's an example here,
you can see foldr plus basically
puts a plus in between each element.
And that's how we're
going to get our factors.
So we're just going to call
max on all of those elements.
Problem 20 is actually very,
very easy in this language.
One of the things that Haskell has,
it has two different kinds of integers.
One is the machine integers.
Which basically fit into 32 or 64 bits.
But it also has something called a BigInt.
So if you go ahead and
take the factorial of 100,
then it will actually print it out for
you.
So here you can see
an example of how that works.
And so once we have that,
then it's actually very easy just
to get the sum of all the digits.
Because all you need to do is take
the modulo 10 and then add those up.
In languages that don't have BigInts
this might actually have been a lot more
difficult.
Because you'd have to figure out our own
way of keeping track of the sizes of
everything.
But because of this,
it makes it very simple and
straightforward just to go ahead and
use these giant numbers.
So now that's these two.
Hope this was a good introduction to
you to see what Haskell looks like.
Again, we'll be seeing a lot more
Haskell in the days to come.