[MUSIC]
This is sort of a more detailed view,
what Workflow System should be doing.
Let me show you some examples, so you
get an idea of what workflows look like.
So here's a workflow as a napkin drawing,
if you like.
As a diagram, as a PowerPoint slide.
This was developed a number of years
ago at UC Davis with one of my
students who was working on workflow
technology and a biologist.
So we don't have to go into
the science details here, but
we see the typical workflow diagram.
There are a bunch of steps,
these steps are kind of fairly
large sized independent functions.
Let's just pick something out there,
something called the chimera check.
So first of all,
what is this workflow called?
It's called Waters, we love our acronyms.
Workflow for Alignment Taxonomy,
Ecology of Ribosomal Sequences.
So this was a PhD student and
Lab of Jonathan Eisen and UC Davis.
So Amber Hartman is the person
who developed this workflow.
And she had these independent tools,
one called Mallard, one called OTUHunter.
They had various bits and pieces that
they needed to chain together for
the full analysis to publish the paper, to
do this study and then publish the paper.
And so
this is the concept diagram that, but
now how do you actually
create a workflow from this?
So Amber was working with one
of my students together and
over the course of pretty much a year,
I think it's almost a year.
They created an executable
form of the diagram.
And it turns out that that executable
form quite directly resembles the napkin
drawing, the conceptual diagram, and it is
implemented in the system called Kepler.
Kepler is a scientific word for
system that also developed
quite a while ago by now 10,
15 years ago ball park.
Based on yet another system,
on top of another system called Ptolemy.
Back in the day, actually I was very
much there when we started this system.
And I had originally suggested that after
the Ptolemy system on which we built,
we should have the Copernicus system.
But Copernicus was a tool that this
group in Berkeley had already used for
something else, for something else,
for compiler for Ptolemy.
And so I just took the next astronomer in
line that came to my mind, was Kepler.
I think the choice of name was fairly
lucky, because it's an easy name to
remember and we got quite well-known for
this product, so like you see here.
So it's a Kepler tool which is really
based on this underlying Ptolemy tool,
you have these boxes they at actors.
So these are computational steps software
components, you can think of them as
a component oriented design of a data
science pipeline or analysis pipeline.
And you grab here from the library
of component that you have.
You drag and
drop the components on the canvas and
then you connect them up and you're done.
So that sounds very compelling and
it works also if your components for
example really work well together and
design together.
But not any two software components
as could easily measure,
you could just stick together.
It has to be some common data performance
as they exchange information and so on.
And then the hard job also
with this kind of system is you better
have these components around to work with.
Creating new components is not so
much fun.
So the system is implementing Java,
so you end up writing Java actors.
And scientist may or
may not be Java hackers,
typically they know more about R and
Python than they know about Java.
But there are such tools out there,
so Kepler's still
out there like it's open source and
there are other systems like it as well.
Okay, so this is something that
again came out of this and
it was then published also in a journal.
And so basically here you see some
of the results, the final plots and
charts that were created for
a particular study.
The workflow itself acts as a kind
of recipe of what was done.
So it's a valuable information or
documentation right there.
It's also executable, although being
a very complex, large software package,
it has its own sort of challenges
when it comes to reproducibility.
So if your versions of Java,
the underlying libraries change,
there's all kinds of version
hell that you might go through.
So if you pick this up
after a couple of years and
want to rerun it, technology has evolved.
And on your system where
you want to run it,
maybe have different versions of
the [INAUDIBLE] and underlying software.
So that's a whole different issue
that we're not dealing with.
Virtual machine technologies
are sometimes used,
container technology such as
docker are sometimes used.
But none of this really fully
solve your problems there.
Okay, so in summary,
there's this workforce systems
that can go from napkin drawings.
That allows you to build
a conceptual workflow that you have,
turn it into something executable,
but it's by no means a trivial matter.
But it is something that has been done,
so we've done quite a few of those.
Here is another workflow again,
first is a napkin drawing,
also done at UC Davis at the time.
This was I think,
if you remember this right,
this was a Matlab script I think and
then we turned into a workflow.
So another one of my students there,
turned it into a workflow again in Kepler,
using a Map Reduce library
that was developed by another
group in Kepler from San Diego.
That group has produced
a Map Reduce library and
we have then used that
library to subscale lab.
What used to be a Matlab script put it
into Kepler and use Map and Reduce.
And so there are lots of these examples.
Here is an example that stitches together
existing components that are written in R.
So assume we have little R scripts
that you want to plug together.
This is an example from a colleague
from Santa Barbara, Matt Jones.
Who has put this together for a project
that he was working on at the time with
the Kruger National Park in South Africa.
And they're basically cobbling
together different R scripts into
a larger workflow.
And then you see this
databases that are queried,
there's some data processing
is done in these R scripts.
Then there's some output at the end and
then what you get is for
example such reports.
And this was I forgot now this had
something to do with I guess hydrology or
monitoring of the environment
I think if I remember, right?
So we did quite a bit of work
with these workflows for
computational science and
maybe let me just pause on this one.
This is one that shows
a more recent workflow that
data curation and data cleaning.
So we've used this workflow
technology in this context.
So for example, imagine that you have
a dataset very much like the one we might
already seen that has specimen data,
by division data.
Let's say you work at a museum,
you work in what do we have here
Chicago the museum, let's say.
And you have a database of all the
specimen that they have in their drawers
and the snakes and
the draw and all of that.
And you want to check whether the
information is of recently good quality.
So you might want to see whether the,
for example,
the species names whether they
follow some controlled vocabulary.
So we have here a step called GNI.
So it's called a scientific
name validator.
So you records go into this workflow and
at a certain step, you compare it
with a controlled vocabulary, and
you see whether your names match
the controlled vocabulary.
If they don't you flag them, maybe you
find the nearest match and suggest a name.
But typically, you want a human to look
at that and whether it's a human or
even if you're afraid from
automatically from change the name.
You better keep a record
of what you've done and
that will be an example of problems, you
want to make sure you have the old value,
the new value and say I've changed.
This value to that value based
on this reference that I used.
For example, this Global Name Index or
IPNI, I think also plant name.
So there's different services out there,
Geolocate is another thing if
you have a lead long coordinate.
And you've a place name, you want to see
whether these lead long coordinates in
the place name match up or not.
If not you flag it, so
you will know something's wrong.
It says this is the lead long and
the place name is this well
that's just impossible in this
service is where he can look this up.
Sometimes log and long is flipped or
maybe the sign is wrong or
something or it's other sources of error.
So we put these different data cleaning
steps together in a workflow here and
this is from a project called Kurator.
This was an early technology
demonstration that we put together and
we used at the time also some little quick
hacks to use some Google Cloud services.
What we did in particular is that the
workflow, created an online spreadsheet.
And in that online spreadsheet,
we summarized what was flagged.
And then this could even automatically
send an email to somebody who
was registered as an expert for
this particular say species or family.
So somebody who is a domain expert
can then look at the records that for
which he or she is an expert.
And then confirm or
reject the changes made by the system.
So it was a very nice demonstration here,
and
then in the end,
pops out your new dataset.
I mean this is a very small snapshot here,
but
you see there's a new dataset coming out.
Also your latitude longitude, for
example, the data's put on a map.
And you will see that certain items
have kind of moved to the right place.
For example, there were a log long
confusion, in this particular case.
And then finally the report that is
generated from this data cleaning,
exercise and workflow,
it serves a providence graph.
So there's a graph that basically shows
what changes happens along the way.
And the providence graph itself is
a knowledge product that you can ask
questions about.
You can say, well did this
particular actor make any changes?
Or did this particular kind of dataset or
location get flagged?
So you can ask questions about that.
[MUSIC]