[MUSIC]
All right, let's have a look
how we install OpenRefine.
So first we go to openrefine.org and
go to the Download page.
And I'm here on a Mac, so I will try and
find the Mac kit for OpenRefine.
So I can use actually here
the Release Candidate 2 that sounds like
the most recent reasonably stable version.
So that's what I'm going to use.
I'm going to click on Mac kit, and
it starts downloading here
about a hundred megabytes.
So we're on a fairly fast connection,
and once this is downloaded,
I can select this and
start the installation.
So I double-click on this,
and we now see OpenRefine
has been made available to us for
installation.
In this case, on the Mac, I'll just drag
it over here to the applications folder.
It notices that there's already another
item there because I installed OpenRefine
previously, so I'm going to say,
I'm going to be brave and say Replace.
And now,
I should have OpenRefine available.
So where is it?
This was from the download.
I can eject that.
I don't need this one, but I can go
here to Spotlight and say openrefine.
And I found it here, double-click.
And it asks me here, it was downloaded
from the Internet, do you trust this?
We do.
And here we go.
And here's OpenRefine.
And here it has actually two collections
there that I worked with earlier.
One thing that's also convenient on
the Mac, if you want to keep that icon in
the dock, you can then say, open Options,
Keep in dock, and then it stays around.
And then we can go inside of any of these
data sets and start working with them.
So as you see, installation is
fairly easy here on the Mac.
[MUSIC]