[MUSIC]
We have now a variant of
the problem where we look at two
taxonomies where the vocabularies
of one level deeper.
Instead of aligning it at
the region level, we say, well,
let the states speak for themselves.
So we say, okay, according to the census,
the US consists of four regions.
But each of those four regions,
we spell it out.
We just spell out the Northeast has these,
the Midwest has that, the South has that,
and the West has that.
Now, for our second taxonomy, NDC,
we say, well, the USA has five regions.
And now we spell out what
the five regions are.
And here's the benefit of this.
Because we went down one level
further into the vocabulary,
sort of looking more closely,
now the articulation we get for free.
It's a long articulation,
but it's totally trivial.
It's all equals, nothing about overlap and
contained in and whatnot.
It's just now the leaves, because we
went further down, it's all clear.
So in a way, this problem is now larger,
because we have more terms
in our vocabularies.
It's going to actually
run a little longer.
But the relationships at the bottom,
in this particular case,
were completely automatically generated,
right?
Because the states are just the same.
So we're going to run this example.
Okay, so this example is called,
so we're going to say
align CEN-NDC-with-DC.
Now, this is going to take I think about
30 seconds or so, or maybe a little less.
The reasoning approach that we use
here is called answer set programming.
You might recall that you've
been using that already.
There it comes,
it's going to have a lot of output data.
And you've used this system,
it's called TLV.
You used it, for example,
to enumerate different repair solutions.
If you have an integrity constraint,
you can use State & Local SQL
to find the violations.
But then you can use this answer set
programming solution to create multiple
worlds, multiple fixes.
And we're kind of using
that same idea here.
But we've computed the solution,
it doesn't look very pretty in ASCII,
does it?
So we're going to show
it as a possible world.
Actually, I'm going to show the taxonomies
first, then I'm going to show the input
visualization, and then I'm
going to show the possible worlds.
Okay, in this case, that's one possible
world, and let's look at that.
So we have just created this new thing,
the newest run done at 11:06.
Let's look at the input first,
so first, the input taxonomies.
What do the input taxonomies look like?
So we have the West, which has these
states, and we have the Midwest, and then
we the Northeast, and we have the South,
and the same thing for the other taxonomy.
So we have the same two taxonomies, but
now expanded one level further down.
What does that give us?
It allows us to now look at
the alignment in this way,
which is kind of very simple now.
So we put them next to each other, and
all the alignments are equalities,
it's very simple.
So Massachusetts according
to this guy is the same
as Massachusetts according to that guy.
New York according to this guy
is the same as that New York.
So at the leaves, so
we point the taxonomies at each other,
the leaves we have complete agreement.
But then over here, what is the South,
and what is the Southeast here?
We don't have, I mean,
this doesn't quite match up, right?
Well, there's some things that line up and
others that don't line up.
If you look at the Midwest,
it looks actually pretty good.
That Midwestern state and those
Midwestern states look exactly the same,
if you look closely.
So hopefully propagates this up and
says the Midwest is actually the same.
But the South or the West is
actually different in the two, okay?
So that's the input alignment.
Again, this one in this case was
completely automatically generated,
because at the states,
there's no controversy.
Now, let's go into
the possible worlds folder,
where we have generated the solution
that the system came up with.
And this is now really very helpful,
because we have now the high
resolution at the state level.
Let's first look at some easy findings.
So, for example, we see here that
the Midwest is completely agreed upon,
so obviously,
we agree about all the individual states.
So at the state level, we always
agree between the two taxonomies.
But now at the regional level,
for the Midwest,
we do also agree, because exactly
the same states are in there.
But for the other regions, we don't.
So again, look at the rightmost part,
at the state level,
we are always in complete agreement,
but what about the half-smokes?
So, for example,
if you are from DC here, again,
both vocabularies agree on what DC is.
But in one taxonomy,
it's in the South, and
in the other case, it's in the Northeast.
And you see that now, right there.
So DC, Maryland, and Delaware
are precisely the overlapping states where
the concepts of South and
Northeast overlap.
So you saw earlier, when we modeled
this whole thing at the regions level,
we couldn't name the overlap.
It didn't have a name,
it's where they overlap.
Now that when we went one level
further down into the state level,
we got a better resolution
of the vocabularies.
And actually, another benefit what we got
is that we got the alignment for free,
it was automatic.
And so we can now sort out our
vocabulary differences and say, well,
if you're in any of these three states,
you can be considered either a Southerner
or a Northeasterner,
depending on who you ask.
Okay, and there are other interests,
for example, New Mexico according to
the Census is in the West, but according
to the NDC, it's not in the West.
In fact,
it's specifically not in the West.
Over here is the West,
it's part of the Southwest.
So you can read all of this information
off of this combined taxonomy.
So I think you see how a tool
like this can be useful.
If you align different vocabularies, it
can sort out differences and reconcile it.
I showed you how this Euler tool
works with a geotaxonomy example.
You see here, this was the resolution
at the regional level.
But once we added the states,
these somewhat cryptic names are now
associated with particular states.
You see here the states
actually drawn in here.
So we talked about New Mexico,
which I think is, these parts,
region R2 is the intersection between
what the Census calls West and
what NDC calls the Southwest.
So these two states, the Southwest and
the West overlap, New Mexico and
Arizona, precisely two states.
If we model it at the level of regions,
we can't pinpoint what they're called.
But we know such a thing must exist
based on the input alignment.
But in our case here,
we had an input alignment that was
completely automatically generated,
which is kind of nicer, and
we get a better resolution at the end.
When input alignments are inconsistent,
we have to diagnose the faults
that can lead to very big graphs.
This is now not the taxonomy alignment.
This is just the diagnostic lattice
that tells us what the problem is,
to pinpoint logic errors.
And we've developed a notation that sort
of focuses on the maximal consistent
subsets and
the minimal inconsistent subsets.
For example,
in a graph that has only ten nodes,
already you get 2 to the 10,
1,024 possible combinations, okay?
So now we're in a situation where you have
given ten inputs, you made ten links, and
the system said no.
Makes you very unhappy,
because you put the effort in
putting those ten connections there.
And the system says, inconsistent,
I'm sorry, it can't do.
I mean, A less than B and B less than A,
that's just not possible.
You can visualize it, but
it's not very helpful.
So we visualize it in a way that
the maximal consistent subsets and
the minimal inconsistent
subsets are highlighted.
And then we can look at those and
sort of scrutinize that and say,
well, where's the mistake?
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]