[MUSIC]
Welcome back, now let's wrap up
what we've learned from this week.
This week, we encountered a powerful
open source data cleaning tool
called OpenRefine.
I demonstrated OpenRefine by exploring its
use with two publicly available data sets,
that is the National Farmer's Market
Database from the US Department of
Agriculture and a crowd sourced collection
of historical restaurant menus provided
by the New York Public Library.
We walk through some basic functions and
transformations of OpenRefine and I also
showed some advanced features relating to
clustering and normalization of names.
As you have seen, OpenRefine is also
fairly easy to install and once installed,
can be used from a web browser.
By working with the materials
from this week and
practicing your OpenRefine skills,
as part of the assignment, you should
now be ready to create an OpenRefine
project, import and profile data, and
apply common transformations and other
mass edits to clean individual columns.
In particular you should be able to use
clustering based methods to normalize data
and bring difference and
tactic variance into economic performance.
You should also be able to document
the changes made to the data using
OpenRefine's operation history.
This is a form of data providence
that we shall encounter again
in more detail towards
the end of this course.
OpenRefine is an open source power tool
that started out as Google refine.
This is fairly well known in the library
and information science community, and
can be applied for many data cleaning
tasks of moderately size data collection.
The ideas and techniques presented
to you can also be applied for
using in other systems.
Since data cleaning is of
great practical importance,
you will probably see more tools like
OpenRefine emerging in the market.
In fact, there are already startup
companies out there developing commercial
products with enhanced and
more scalable features similar to
those we encountered in OpenRefine.
Next week, we will move on from data
cleaning operations on individual columns.
And we look at logical constraints
between multiple columns and data tables.
We will work with
the relational data model.
[MUSIC]