[MUSIC]
Welcome back.
Now let's briefly wrap up
what we covered this week.
In the second week, we talked about the
roots of regular expressions in computer
science theory, and we learned about
practical regular expressions as found for
example in R, Python, Java or OpenRefine.
And we then exercised our
regular expression skills
on an interactive website that provides
you with immediate feedback so
you can better understand
how your expressions work.
By learning what regular expressions and
exercising your hands-on skills,
you should now be able to situate
regular expressions among other
formal languages in
computer science theory.
And to define simple regular expressions
for example in Python, to extract or
match data and check whether it conforms
to a certain desired or undesired format.
Next week,
we will learn about a popular power tool
for data cleaning called OpenRefine.
Regular expressions are only
one of many features and
capabilities that OpenRefine offers for
syntax based data cleaning.
[MUSIC]