[MUSIC]
Hello, and welcome back to Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
In previous lectures we looked
at individual pieces of a larger
data cleaning lifecycle.
We started with syntax-based
data transformation and
cleaning using regular expressions and
then using open refine.
We then moved on to data integrity
checking at the schema or
semantic level where we can look
not only at individual columns but
at complex relations and data tables
as a whole and their interconnections.
In the following lectures,
we take a step back and
look at the data life cycle again.
When researchers and
data scientists analyzed their data,
they often need to
automate multiple steps.
Automation can happen even for
the data cleaning itself.
But certainly for complex computational
analysis, you want to use a workflow
system, or script-based approach, say
Python or R, to automate your analysis.
So the following lectures will
introduce basic notions of workflows,
focusing in particular and
scientific workflow automation.
Another aspect that is related
to automation is providence.
That is the origin and processing history
of data that comes out of the workflow.
This will be the topic of future lectures.
Okay, let's jump right into
the first lecture on workflows.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]