Hello everyone.
Welcome to CS 421.
Today we're going to talk
about the Interpreter
Activity, and as always,
we hope that you will have
gone through this either by
yourself or with some friends
before watching this video.
Your objectives are to be
able to read the source code for
a simple interpreter and
to understand how
everything works.
We're going to talk about
lifting and how we make
actual Haskell functions work
on our interpreter types,
and then we're going to add
a few features, namely,
we're going to add variables
and comparison operations.
Now first let's talk
about the types.
We have two levels for this;
we have a type to represent
the source code
that the programmer
types in and that's going to be
the Exp type from lines
five through seven.
We're going to start with
two kinds of expressions;
the integer expression and
the integer operation expression.
We're going to have one type
to represent the output,
that's Val, and we're going
to start off with
just integer values,
but we'll add more later.
Finally, to be able to
add variables later,
we're going to have
an environment type.
When we have a variable,
we need some way to look up
what the corresponding value is.
The type on the
slide is listed as
list of pair with
string and expression,
and that's a bug because we
want to have a value instead.
Now there are some languages
which might allow you to
put expression inside of
variables, that's pretty rare.
Let's talk about
how we're going to
make Haskell functions work
with the types we have
for our interpreter.
One way to do that
is first I create
a dictionary to map
strings to the actual
Haskell functions,
so one variation of the
type is given above.
It's very similar to
the environment type,
but it remaps strings to
integer error, integer error,
integer instead of to value,
so this allows the programmer
to specify slash and
their source code and we get
the actual function div
out the other side.
Now, to make these
functions work with values,
we have what we call
lifting operation.
You see this on line
six through eight,
though we have a
function as the input,
which is a Haskell function,
and then we input
two integer values,
and then we basically extract
the actual integers
out of the IntVals,
apply them to the
function and then
rewrap that into another IntVal.
The bug is on line 8,
so you see we're
returning a zero here,
and that's a numeric type
or IntVal is a Val type,
you can't have two separate types
coming out on the same
function like that.
Once you have this thing working,
it allows you to say things like,
liftIntOp star and
then give it IntVal 3
and IntVal 7 and give
it IntVal 21 back.
Now, if you want to
take care of that bug,
there is two ways
you could do with.
Line 8 gives what you might
call the JavaScript way,
where if something
breaks, it just says,
oh well and keeps going,
so maybe just return a zero
and hope for the best.
A little bit better
is to have an error message
like you would on line 9,
so you'll pick one of
these two lines to use,
and the combined is
actually going to give you
a warning that the
code is unreachable.
This is because we only
have one value type,
which means line 7
is going to handle
every possible thing you could
call this function
with at the time.
Now line zero,
there's another way
we could have done this;
we can be a little bit
more general and say
that this works for all
types that are integrals,
integral just means you could
turn it into a fraction.
It's more general than what
we need for our interpreter,
but well, who knows,
maybe we want to extend it later.
Now we get to the heart of
the interpreter, which is eval.
The eval takes your expression
in the environment,
the assignment of variables and
then gives you back the
corresponding values.
This is the thing that's actually
going to run your program.
The line 1, we have
integer expressions,
we just return the
corresponding integer value.
We've already talked about this
that we are not just
going to return
integers because we expect to
have other kinds of values later.
The lines three through seven,
we have integer
operation expressions,
so we have two
sub-expressions, e1 and e2.
This is a big thing
that you're going to
find in the language class,
is that the value
of an expression
is determined by composing
the values of its subexpressions.
When I say value,
I can mean other properties too,
like the type and the pattern
is almost always the same.
We're going to look at
the subexpressions first,
and then we're going to
combine those results.
We do that here on
lines four and five,
we call eval on e1 and
e2 to get v1 and v2.
We look up the operator
and intOps from line 6,
and you see that
they're returning
a just f, or assuming that.
The reason that lookup does this,
so if you look up something in
a dictionary and it's not there,
you really have three
options to deal with it;
option 1 is to throw
an error message and then
the programmer has to put a
try-catch block around that.
Option 2 is to return
a default value,
which is actually a
terrible thing to do
unless that really is what
you want to have happen.
The other way is to
use this maybe type.
So you return a nothing
if it's not there and
adjust with the thing
if you found it.
Now, I'm circumventing
that on line 6 because I'm
directly pattern-matching
against just
f. So if the lookup
returns a nothing,
you'll get a runtime error.
This is basically the same thing
as throwing an exception.
Now, this can be
appropriate if you are
generating this expression
problematically
so you know by construction,
as we said that the expression
is going to be correct.
Finally, line 7, we call it lift
operation on f. In this bug 3,
you see there's e1 and e2 there,
it should be v1 and v2.
Let's add a feature
to our language now.
We can start the variables
since they are easy to add.
First, we have to
modify the Exp type.
We add one new constructor
to represent variable
expressions.
Next, we have to add a
corresponding clause to
val to process those
variable expressions.
Line 1 does the lookup,
and the result can be
either that we found
the variable and got a just back,
in which case we return
the value we get
picked to the color,
or else we might get a nothing.
Again, we have two choices
how to handle that;
we could just do it the way
shell scripting languages do
it and give it a default value.
In our case, we'll
have it return a
zero and hope for the best.
This of course, is
terrible language design
if you want reliability.
The better way is to simply
return an error message.
Now, let's add comparison
operations to the language.
We need a new constructor
for Val since we will have
both integer and Boolean
values and the language.
We also need a new
constructor for
Exp to represent
comparison operations.
Now, we would really
have liked to use
the intOps dictionary to
store these comparison
operations,
but a comparison operator has
a different type than
the arithmetic operator,
it outputs a Boolean
instead of an integer.
Because of this, we need
a separate dictionary and
separate lifting operation
to deal with them.
Now, other than the types
and the specific names,
the code here uses
the same idea as
the liftIntOp code we had before.
One nice thing though,
now that we have more than one
constructor and our value type,
the compiler warnings
will go away.
Finally, we can add
the clause to eval.
It has the same structure
as a clause for intOpExp,
only now we're using
the CompOpEx dictionary
and the liftCompOp functions.
That will be all for this video.
In the next activity,
we'll show you how to
add functions to your language.