Hello and welcome back.
In the last lesson,
we talked about variables and
the different properties
that they could have.
In this part, we're going to talk
about the different ways we can pass
the variable into, or
sometimes even out of a function.
And when you're done with this video,
you'll be able to explain these five
kinds of parameter passing styles.
Since you can read, I'm just going to
pause and let you read it, and
not read it to you.
Now there are two major classes
of parameter passing styles,
the eager styles and the lazy styles.
For the eager styles,
we'll use this running example.
Suppose to look sort of like but let's
pretend we have variable reassignment.
Now the terms parameter in argument
are often used interchangeably, but for
this video, I'm going to make
a distinction between them.
So our parameter will be the variable
listed in the function declaration,
like the x, y, and z above.
And the argument's going to be a value
passed into the function by the function
call, like a, b, and
a plus b on the bottom.
Our first style is called a value.
It's one of the most common choices
because it's really efficient.
The argument to a function is evaluated
before a function call happens and
the resulting value gets placed
into the parameter of the function.
Values in the computer typically one
word such as an integer or float or
a pointer to a larger structure.
And the computations that generate
these values are usually larger.
So since we intend to
use the value anyway,
it just makes sense to
do the evaluation first.
Now there are two problems with this.
One problem, and
this might not be obvious at first,
is that we may in fact not always
want to evaluate an argument.
Now here's an example of
a projection function, pi1,
that takes two arguments and
returns the first, ignoring the second.
Mathematically, the function call
here where pi1 is called on 5 and
foo should just return 5, but
in the Call By Value language,
this will crash since the second
argument causes an infinite loop.
Now this case is rare enough that most
programming language designers don't care,
will instead say that the program
shouldn't be writing code that does
things like that in the first place,
and they kind of have a point.
Here's a running example
using Call By Value.
The a gets copied to y and
b gets copied to y.
And a+b gets evaluated to 30 and
it's the 30 that gets copied to z.
Inside the function,
x gets 30 times 30 time 20 and y gets 5.
When the function 2 returns, a still has
the value 10 and b still has the value 20.
Now sometimes we don't want
that kind of behavior.
Sometimes we want the function to
have the ability to assign into
the variable we pass into it.
Or perhaps the value is so large we want
to pass an appointer to the object rather
than a copy of the object itself.
This is classic call by reference.
Now the advantage is speed,
especially for a large object.
And also the ability to
cause side effects or
modifications in the variables
that were passed in.
If indeed you consider
that to be an advantage.
You kind of know how we feel
about that in this course.
Now going to our running example, you can
see how this differs from call by value.
A and
x share the same memory location now and
this is the scene like what we talked
about in the variable binding video.
Similarly, for b and y,
a+b is not a variable, so
it's getting evaluated like call by value.
When x is assigned to 30 times 30
times 20, both x and a get that value.
When y is assigned 5,
then b also gets that value.
Now the C language allows for
call by reference, but
you have to pass in a pointer explicitly.
It's clear from the syntax that you're
offering the function a chance to modify
your variable if that's what it wants.
C++ allows you to blur
this syntactically and
I'm not sure that this
is always a good thing.
So for example, look at this code,
inc(i) will return 11 and
the i retains its original value.
The inc function is using
call by value now, but
let's change that to call by reference.
Now the incrementation happens in main,
as well.
You might think that this cout will
now output to 11's and depending on
the compiler you could be right, but
the left arrow operators are functions and
some compilers will evaluate the second
i before returning the inc i.
So output might still be 11 and
10 even though i roles have the value
10 when the expression is done.
The last eager style is very strange
is called call by result and
sometimes known as call by value-result.
The idea behind this is that the function
can modify one of its parameters and after
the function returns, that value is copied
back into the argument that was passed in.
Sometimes called the poor
man call by result.
Because it does similar things.
It's sometimes called as
a poorer mans call by reference,
because of the similar things.
In a running example,
we have a copied to x and b copied to y,
just like in call by value.
X is assigned a 30 times 30 times 20 and
y is assigned a 5 just
like in call by value.
Foo returns a+b, which is 10 plus 20.
But after the return, a and
b will get updated with the values
that were stored into x and y.
So it's kind of like a delayed
reaction called by reference.
A normally used case for
is to have functions that
initialize variables for you.
So if you've ever done Windows
programming in the late 90s,
you'll see an initialization
functions that do this kind of thing.
As for programming languages,
this feature's kind of rare.
Prolog kind of acts like this due to
using unification to populate variables.
But C# has this explicitly through
what they call out parameters.
So now let's talk about the lazy styles.
Lazy styles do not evaluate the arguments
unless it's necessary to do so
to return the value of the function.
First of these is called call by name.
In this style, arguments are substituted
for the parameters into the function body
as if someone did a search and
replace operation.
This means that if a computation
happens not to use
a parameter the corresponding
argument never gets evaluated.
So in the pi1 example we had before,
the call to foo now works as we hoped.
Returns five without
risking an infinite loop.
It's not all good news though.
Consider this example.
Here, foo has three parameters,
x, y and z.
This is x and y twice each but
it does not touch the z at all.
So I mean it calls foo with 10 plus 10 for
x and
20 plus 20 for y and
a looping occurs in foo z.
Since c doesn't occur in the body of foo,
it never gets evaluated, but
both copies of x get
replaced by 10 plus 10.
So that computation happens twice,
similarly with the 20 plus 20 replacing y.
The call by name is not used very often,
you will see it in the c pre-processing
language when you use number to find for
things, and the scripting language
TCL has some limited support for it.
The final style we'll talk
about today is call by need.
This is the style that Haskell uses.
It's like call by name, but
we will first wrap a data structure
around it called a thunk.
Now a thunk has three states.
Unevaluated, evaluated,
and pending evaluation.
When we pass a thunk to a function,
all copies of a parameter refer
to the same thunk in memory.
The first time a thunk is evaluated,
the code gets replaced by the result.
The second and
following times the thunk gets evaluated,
and it just returns a value.
So think of it as web caching for
variables.
So here's what happens with foo and
main, x and y get thunks.
The first x computes 10 plus 10,
and the second x just returns 20.
The first y computes 20 plus 20.
The second y just returns 40.
And the z is never used,
so it's never evaluated.
The call by need is optimal in that
a parameter will only be evaluated at most
one time, and
only if it's actually needed.
There's usually some overhead in
setting up the thunk if you're
doing this in an eager language, but
languages like Haskell are designed
to make this very efficient.
And so that's it for
the different parameter
passing styles and for variables.