[MUSIC]
So what we mean by filtering is
actually quite a bit different from
what we saw earlier from
the data log filter.
That one was really just a very
high level switch in that system.
Here, filtering is really
the way we think of it.
We run a query,
we get a table as an answer.
But in the table,
maybe only certain roles you want to keep.
And this is the where clause.
Okay, so for example, if we run the.
This is a table, want to see.
Select * from the visited table, visited.
Let's see what's in there.
Okay, that's the visited table.
But maybe you're interested in only one of
the sites, say DR-1 as in th example here.
Then we would say where.
Okay, I'm going to highlight again
the SQL keywords to make it clear.
So this is where clause
in SQL where I can say,
I can specify now a condition on the row.
These conditions are very similar to
the conditions we have in our data log
rule in the body.
We'll have a constraint that this
equals that, that's greater than this,
this is not equal to that.
So here we want to say okay, we want to
say maybe that the site equals DR1.
And then we only get the DL1 tuples.
Remember the story about
the case insensitivity?
Well, if I put DR1 here, I get nothing.
Because of course, the selection in here,
the condition, where a side equals this,
is case sensitive.
We're looking at a particular data value,
right?
So this really makes a difference,
whereas it doesn't
make a different whether I write select
from where uppercase or lowercase.
That does not make a difference, okay?
All right, and so here's a visual
representation of what's happening.
We can think of the system going
through the table, row by row and
checking whether the condition,
the where clause, is satisfied, and
if it is, you keep the result.
And then there's actually another feature,
it's a projection here.
Let's look at this.
So here we said select * from
visited where the site is this.
So we want to sort of now we're drilling
down, we're looking only at this site.
But maybe we only want the id
instead of the whole table.
You see we get three columns here.
Three rows and three columns.
Maybe we only interested in the id.
So we would just say select id from
this and now we get this answer.
So in a way first we go
through table row by row.
And the where clause tells us which row
to keep and which row to throw out.
And when we're done with that, we saw
well which column should I focus on?
And that's what that select id is for.
Again, so there's a lot going on.
Again, it's a little
bit of a crash course.
It's either very boring or
very challenging for you, depending
on whether you do or don't know this.
So but this is very nice that
we see here that the kind of tool phases
of how the scale statement is executed.
So first with with the where statement
here which filters the rows.
And the ones were down there,
the select statement,
which really should be called project
because we're projecting on a column.
This is rather unfortunate
terminology of SQL here.
It's a projection.
We're projecting only on the first column,
throwing away the second and
the fifth column.
And that's how we arrive at this result.
So this is really critical that you get
a good understanding of how a basic SQL
query works like select from where.
You can then put the condition in
the where clause that selects the rows can
be much more complicated
than just an equality.
You can say for example well I
want the site to be this, but
the date to be less than that.
And since we use an ISO date,
it actually works.
The normal comparison works here,
even the string comparison
will work here for dates.
Now if you compare dates you have to be
very careful whether you compare strings,
then they better be
an isoformic which just works.
Or if they're enough strings,
then hopefully you use the whatever
built in support for comparing dates.
But here,
again we go into the visitor table,
we're focusing on the side,
the R1 and also we only keep the row.
If it was done before January 1st, 1930.
And sure enough we got 1927 dates here.
If I were to remove the dated constraint,
I get also a third row with 1932.
If the input table format is
sort of messed up or dirty,
then a scale will be very unhappy
in giving you the wrong result.
So that's why with a typical data cleaning
pipeline, you would first have done
something like open refine or maybe
regular expression based replacement,
matching and replacement,
otherwise you're in trouble.
In this particular case,
is this a string comparison?
It works because the ISO standard
was carefully chosen to put year
then month then day, so that a regular
string comparison will get the job done.
If you use any of the other date formats,
you could write special
code that compares them.
But since pretty much any system has
a string comparison function built in,
why not choose a representation so that
it works for free, in a way, for dates.
I'm sure one of the rationales
why the ISO standards
organization has chosen that format.
[MUSIC]
[SOUND]