[MUSIC]
We're going to go to this website
from Southwest Carpentry.
And they have a nice small
database called surveydb,
and we're going to walk through
some of these examples.
So in particular, if you walk through
here, you see further details, and
I'm going to do some of that right now.
So I'm going to use, for this part,
I'm going to use my friend, the Emacs or
AquaMax editor, since that will help me
to keep track of what I've seen already.
So we're going to run a couple
of queries that I have here.
So we're going to start.
Maybe I'm going to do it like this, I'm
going to open two windows, side-by-side,
and one of them will
have the SQLite running.
Or you could also use the terminal.
Again, I'm going to cheat
a little bit by using Emacs here.
I can go more easily back and
forth in the history, okay?
And we have to first find surveydb.
Let's see if I have this available here,
anywhere on the desktop.
So I'm going to go to a sub folder,
which I hope has the serverdb in it.
Now here it is, okay?
So this is going to be
my shell on the right.
And on the left, I'm going to have
the examples that I'm going to go through.
So, in order to start the SQLite system,
again, we need to say sqlite3.
And if you already have a database, for
example here we might have downloaded,
actually let me do this here.
I'm going to download this database,
why don't I do this right now.
Download this database.
Okay, here it is and
it's now in my Downloads folder.
So I should probably,
so where are we here?
I want to copy from
the Downloads folder survey.db.
I'm going to copy it
into my current folder.
So as you've seen how that works.
And now I can run sqlite3
with that survey.db.
Okay, so
I'm using the latest version of SQLite.
As you see, it's from 2017.
Help for usage hints, so
that's not a bad idea.
And maybe the first thing I want to do is
I want to look at what tables are there.
So is there a command that
tells me what tables are there?
[MUSIC]