[MUSIC]
Welcome back, now let's wrap up what
we have learned about SQL queries and
integrity constraints this week.
Now overall data cleaning life cycle
we have moved from this enthectic and
pedal level data cleaning through
the logical or semantic level.
First using data log as our main language.
In this week, we have done a recap or
crush course depending on
your prior knowledge on SQL.
We have seen how to formulate general
queries in SQL as well as written special
queries for
identifying integrity violations.
This is also the subject
of the assignment.
In future lectures we will then zoom out
and look at the larger data cleaning and
analysis workflows.
[MUSIC]