[MUSIC]
Hello, and welcome to week 1 of Theory and
Practice of Data Cleaning.
This week,
I will give you a general overview and
introduction to the topics
covered in this course.
Specifically, this week we will talk about
what is data cleaning, or data wrangling,
as it's sometimes called.
Why is it important, and where does
it fit in the larger data science and
analytics picture?
We will also try to clarify
what data quality means
by linking it to the notion of fitness for
use, and
by exploring a few data quality
dimensions, and point you to associated
optional readings if you'd like to learn
more about some of these dimensions.
Finally, I will mention the tools we
are going to be using in this course.
After all, the title of this course is
Theory and Practice of Data Cleaning.
After this first week, I hope that you
understand the role of data cleaning in
the larger data management and analysis
life cycle, and that you are able to spot
certain data quality issues and associate
them with a quality dimension and,
possibly, a tool or approach that could
help improve the quality of data.
In the second week, we will also
have our first hands-on assignment.
But first things first,
let's jump right into the first lecture.
[MUSIC]